<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The novels of Dom Francisco de Quevedo Villegas, knight of the order of St. James Faithfully Englished. Whereunto is added, The marriage of Belphegor, an Italian novel. Translated from Machiavel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S369A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219865</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831312</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35775</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35775)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2041:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The novels of Dom Francisco de Quevedo Villegas, knight of the order of St. James Faithfully Englished. Whereunto is added, The marriage of Belphegor, an Italian novel. Translated from Machiavel.</title>
                  <author>Quevedo, Francisco de, 1580-1645. aut</author>
                  <author>Salas Barbadillo, Alonso Jerónimo, 1581-1635.</author>
                  <author>Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527. Novella di Belfagor. English. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Starkey, at the Miter in Fleet-street, near Temple-bar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With two preliminary advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: The novels of Dom Francisco de Quevedo, the night-adventurer.</note>
                  <note>Part 1 running title reads: The night-adventurer.</note>
                  <note>"The marriage of Belphegor" has caption title on p. 135; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Formerly Wing (2nd ed.) Q192.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35775:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NOVELS OF Dom <hi>Franciſco de Quevedo Villegas,</hi> Knight of the Order of St. <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully Engliſhed.</p>
            <p>Where unto is added, The Marriage of <hi>Belphegor,</hi> An <hi>ITALIAN</hi> Novel.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated from <hi>Machiavel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Starkey,</hi> at the <hi>Miter</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Temple-bar,</hi> 1671.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35775:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35775:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:35775:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35775:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>THe end of moſt Prefaces, being to beg ſubmiſsively the favour and attention of a Reader, who is moſt commonly inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, had put me ſo out of love with them, that I was reſolv'd to make none for my <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> whoſe Nation or Wit ſeldom uſe to go a begging: But the Book-ſeller not well pleaſed that his Book ſhould want a leaf in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which others have, is very earneſt to have me ſay ſomething of one, whoſe Name ſpeaks enough for himſelf: <hi>Quevedo,</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is my Author, and his pleaſant <hi>Viſions,</hi> which have of late ſo diverted you, were the productions of the ſame brain as theſe <hi>Novels:</hi> 'Tis true, there will be one advantage wanting to them, and that is, that they have not met with one that could dreſs them ſo well in the Engliſh habit, as the <hi>Viſions</hi> did: But truly, in that beſides their misfortune, you muſt blame the ſullenneſs of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who had ſo affected an humour this time, as not to be perſwaded to change his Scene, or lay
<pb facs="tcp:35775:4"/>aſide his Native cuſtoms. It would have been eaſie to have changed the <hi>Prado</hi> into <hi>Saint James's Park;</hi> but then what ſhould we have done with the Guittar, which is ſo abſolutely unſeparable from a <hi>Spaniards</hi> court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Night? the cuſtoms of hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries being much to give occaſſion to <hi>Night-Adventures.</hi> It would have been ſomewhat uncouth, to have brought him to walk the Streets of <hi>London,</hi> where he would ſee no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy but a few Wenches, and the Conſtable with his Watch, ready to ſpoil all at every turning. This I thought fit to ſay as well for the Author, as for the Tranſlator, but moſt of all for the Book-ſeller; For I believe the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will find more ſatisfaction, and a greater Apologie for the faults; if any, in the reading of the Book, than of the Preface. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:35775:4"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books Printed this year <hi>1670.</hi> for <hi>John Starkey</hi> Book-ſeller, at the <hi>Miter</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe <hi>Jeſuits Morals,</hi> collected by a Doctor of the Colledge of <hi>Sorbon</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> who hath faithfully extracted them out of the Jeſuits own Books which are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the permiſſion and approbation of the Superiors of their Society. Written in <hi>French,</hi> and exactly tranſlated into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Folio, price bound 12 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſilica Chymica &amp; Praxis Chymiatrice,</hi> or <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Practical Chymiſtry,</hi> in three Treatiſes; being a Tranſlation of <hi>Oſwald Crollius</hi> his <hi>Royal Chymiſtry;</hi> augmented an enlarged by <hi>John Hartman.</hi> To which is added his Treatiſe of <hi>Signatures of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal things,</hi> or a true and lively Anatomy of the greater and leſſer World. As alſo the <hi>Practice of Chymiſtry</hi> of <hi>John Hartman,</hi> M. D. augmented and enlarged by his Son, with conſiderable Additions; all faithfully Engliſhed by a Lover of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry, in Folio, price bound 10 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Relation of three <hi>Embaſſies,</hi> from his Majeſty <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to the Great Duke of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> performed by the
<pb facs="tcp:35775:5"/>Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Carliſte,</hi> in the years 1663. and 1664. Written by an Attendant on the Embaſſies, in Octavo, price bound 4 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Relation of the Siege of Candia,</hi> from the firſt Expedition of the <hi>French Forces,</hi> to its Surrender the 27th. of <hi>September</hi> 1669. Written in <hi>French</hi> by a Gentleman who was a Voluntier in that Service, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Engliſhed. In Octavo, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preſent State of the <hi>United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> as to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Laws, Forces, Riches, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Cuſtoms, Revenue, and Territory of the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Collected out of divers Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors by <hi>W. A.</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</hi> In Twelves, price bound 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> the ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accidence Commenc'd Grammar,</hi> and ſupply'd with ſufficient Rules; or a new and eaſie Method for the learning the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Tongue.</hi> The Author <hi>John Milton.</hi> In Twelves, price bound 8 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Relation of the Coaſts of Africk called Guinnee,</hi> with a Deſcription of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Manners, and Cuſtoms of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants; of the Productions of the Earth, and the Merchandiſe and Commodities it affords, with ſome Hiſtorical Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:35775:5"/>on the Coaſts, being collected in a <hi>Voyage</hi> made by the <hi>Sieur Villault Eſcuyer Sieur de Bellefond</hi> in the years 1666. and 1667. faithfully Engliſhed. In Twelves, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> the ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>A Guide for <hi>Conſtables, Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Overſeers</hi> of the Poor, <hi>Surveyors</hi> of the High-ways, <hi>Treaſurers</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-ſtock, <hi>Maſters</hi> of the Houſe of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>Baylifs</hi> of Mannors, <hi>Toll-takers</hi> in Fairs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhewing the extent and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the ſeveral Offices; Collected by <hi>George Meriton,</hi> price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> the ſecond Edition, with additions.</p>
            <p>A Relation of the <hi>French Kings</hi> late <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition</hi> into the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> in the years 1667. and 1668. with an Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction diſcourſing his Title thereunto, and an Account of the Peace between the two Crowns, made <hi>May</hi> 2. 1668. Engliſhed by <hi>G. H.</hi> In Twelves, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Voyage of Italy,</hi> or a Compleat Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney through <hi>Italy;</hi> in two parts: with the <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> and the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the chief <hi>Towns, Churches, Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Villas, Gardens, Pictures, Statues, Antiquities;</hi> as alſo of the <hi>Intereſt, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Riches, Force,</hi> &amp;c. of all the
<pb facs="tcp:35775:6"/>
               <hi>Princes,</hi> with inſtructions concerning <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> By <hi>Richard Laſſels</hi> Gent. who tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled through <hi>Italy</hi> five times as Tutor to ſeveral of the Engliſh Nobility: <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humum.</hi> Corrected and ſet forth by his old Friend and Fellow-traveller <hi>S. W.</hi> Never before extant. In Twelves, price bound 4 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The preſent State of <hi>France,</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Orders, Dignities</hi> and <hi>Charges</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom:</hi> Newly corrected and put into a better method than formerly: writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>French,</hi> and faithfully <hi>Engliſhed,</hi> in twelves, price bound 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paradiſe Regained: A Poem in Four Books,</hi> to which is added, <hi>Samſon Agoniſtes,</hi> a Dram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Poem; the Author <hi>John Milton.</hi> In Octavo, price bound 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> in which is handled the moſt rare and incomparable Wonder of Nature, in tranſmuting Metals, <hi>viz.</hi> how the intire ſubſtance of Lead was in one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment tranſmuted into Gold obrizon, with an exceeding ſmall particle of the true Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophick Stone, at the <hi>Hague</hi> in the year 1666. Written in Latin by <hi>John Frederic Helvetius,</hi> Doctor and Practitioner at the <hi>Hague.</hi> Faithfully Engliſhed. In Twelves, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="stories">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35775:6"/>
            <head>THE NOVELS OF Dom <hi>Franciſco de Quevedo,</hi> The Night-Adventurer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will be needleſs in the beginning of this Work, to uſe an Invocation of <hi>Apollo;</hi> for ſince we do deſcribe the actions of one, who was at feude with thoſe beams of light, which make the happineſs of other Mortals, if we did require the aſſiſtance of any of the Divinities of the Fabels, it would rather be that of <hi>Diana,</hi> whoſe pale rays preſide over the gloomy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35775:7"/>dark ſhades of the Night. But leaving there the Stars, we muſt make our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to ſomething more black than thoſe Clouds, through which their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences are ſtill preceptible, and I think Ink is the beſt thing we can hit upon; for indeed can there be any thing from which we may expect a more favourable aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſince its deep black is the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd Liverys of our <hi>Adventurer?</hi> 'Tis true, Paper will have ſome reaſon to complain, to ſee its whiteneſs ſoiled, and its evenneſs disfigured with ſo many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Characters, but I muſt deſire it to put up this injury among the many others, which it patiently endures every day, from the an infinity of ſcribling Authors, whoſe temerity and ignorance are eternally prompting them to affront it. Hail then thou black Dye, by whoſe means Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals renown and fame is both illuſtrated and blur'd; help us to deſcribe the actions of a tenebrious Knight, the wanderer of Church-yards, the camerade of <hi>Bats</hi> and <hi>Owls;</hi> but let us not be too nice in our ſtile, for it's Truth from which we intend to borrow our Ornaments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Talavera</hi> a conſiderable City in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35775:7"/>Kingdom of <hi>Toledo,</hi> and ſituated upon the banks of the golden <hi>Tagus,</hi> was the place where our Heros firſt ſaw light; he was of a noble Family, which had no blemiſh either in its Honour or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: In his firſt Infancy, his houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Scene of ſorrow, for his Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing engaged in a duel, dyed gallantly, and left his Son an ample inheritance of fame and honour; his Mother ſurpaſſing all the VViddows, who now a dayes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford to ſtay till their mourning be over, till they engage in new amours, prevented even the news of her Widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood by a ſecond Marriage.</p>
            <p>Our Cavalier was the youngeſt of three Brothers, and by conſequent deſigned for the Church; his name at firſt was only <hi>Don Diego,</hi> but in time by his conduct he acquired the Sirname of <hi>Lucifugne,</hi> or enemy of the Light. The Church who takes care of her Children was ſo fond of him, that ſhe nouriſhed him from his tender years, with the ſweet milk of divers rich Benefices, which from time to time were conferr'd on him, whereof ſome requiring his reſiding at <hi>Toledo,</hi> made that a neceſſity in him, which elſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35775:8"/>would have been a choice. For it is one of the deliciouſeſt places in the VVorld; but whether it were that he was ſoon glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the abundant pleaſures of the place, or that the obligation of their taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them took away the greateſt part of their reliſh; he ſtayed not long there, but having attained the 20th. year of his age, he diſpoſed of his Benefices into other peoples hands, ſtill reſerving to himſelf conſiderable penſions upon them; with the aid of which, and of his own Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, he made up a Revenue of 6 or 700 pound a year: Thus provided againſt Fortune, and full fraught with the expectation of that variety which young peoples vagabond inclinations do moſt run after, he came to <hi>Madrid,</hi> the chief Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the ordinary reſidence of the King and Court. There he ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf in that part of the Town, which was moſt ſuitable to his capricious humour, which was that which was leaſt frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in a by-Street where few people did come. The houſe he bought was pretty large, and ſo capable of being divided into two parts, with all neceſſary apartments to each; the one he reſerv'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35775:8"/>for himſelf, and the other for his friends; which laſt he furniſh'd very neatly and modiſhly; as for his own, he order'd it according to his extravagant humour. Firſt, he took down all the upper ſtories, as being uſeleſs to one who was reſolved to keep as much under ground and in the dark as it was poſſible. Secondly, he cauſed all the VVindows to be ſtopt up, not leaving the leaſt cranny for the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams to peep through; then he hung all the VValls of it with black; in a word, 'twas rather a ſepulchre for the Dead, than a habitation of the Living. He was moſt paſſionate for the art of Muſick, taking a ſingular delight in playing upon his Guit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and ſinging to it; and in this he was ſo great a Maſter, that there were but very few that could compare with him; and indeed his excellence in this Art, and Poetry, made up the greateſt part of his ambition; for he was very well pleaſed with his own condition, not at all moved at other peoples vanity or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and ſo far from courting fortune to an encreaſe of his, that all his deſign was only to enjoy himſelf and his friends in his own ſingular way; he ſeldom or never
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35775:9"/>ſtirr'd out in the day time, giving all that to Muſick and ſleep; as ſoon as it was dark, and that there was no diſtinguiſhing of objects, then did he ſet out for a walk, which he alwayes perform'd without any other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany or protection than that of his Sword, a Rondach or Buckler, and his Guittar, and in this Equipage walking all night, he met with great variety of Adventures, ſome good, ſome bad, but ſtill ending glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and to his Honour. If it pleaſe you, Reader, to ſurceaſe your other occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, which it may be are as idle as the relation of his Adventures will be, I will recite ſome of them to you, and do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe before hand, that they ſhall be both diverting and profitable.</p>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35775:9"/>
               <head>Adventure the firſt.</head>
               <p>IN the middle of the VVinter, and of the moneth of <hi>January,</hi> a ſeaſon in which the Nights are a great deal longer than the Dayes, and ſo cold, that the moſt fiery completions are ready to freeze if they chance to be abroad: <hi>Don Diego</hi> being weary of ſitting at home all alone, reſolv'd about eleven of the Clock at Night to take a turn in the Streets of <hi>Madrid;</hi> he took his Guittar, and in his way playing ſome Sarabands, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſinging to it, had gone through a great many Lanes and By-places, when at laſt being come to a very ſolitary quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Town, he ſtop'd a little to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider where he was, and looking up heard a Caſement open, and a Voice call him with the inviting noiſe of <hi>iſt, iſt:</hi> He whoſe heart was alwayes enclined to new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries in Nocturn Adventures, drew near and heard a whiſpering Voice ſay theſe VVords: <hi>If it be you that left this place laſt Night, with ſo many marks of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſatisfaction, why come you again to Night ſo late? Don Diego</hi> was a little ſurprized at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35775:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo pleaſant a queſtion; but immediately recollecting himſelf, anſwered;<hi>'Tis I, I am the ſame Man, open the door;</hi> as ſoon as he had ſpoke, the door was opened, and he heard ſome body bid him tread very ſoftly; he obeys, and following a perſon that led him by the hand, did begin already to thank his genius, for prompting him to the quick acceptance of the good fortune which he thought attended him within. After he had paſſed two or three Doors, and as many Entries, he came at laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Room, at the entrance of which, inſtead of the amorous Embraces which he expected, he found himſelf ſeized by three or four ſtrong Men, borne down to the ground, and diſarmed; The place where he was, was a Parlour; on the table were two lights, and at the further end of the Room he perceived an old Man, of a venerable aſpect, ſitting in a Chair, who riſing up as he drew near, (led by his Jaylors) broke forth into theſe words, which he proffer'd with a hoarſe Voice and a threatning Countenance. VVhy, ſaid he, (ſpeaking to thoſe that held him) have you brought him alive into my preſence, and why did not you Strangle him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35775:10"/>Then, looking upon the Priſoner; Barbarous wretch, ſaid he, for I cannot believe thou wer't ever iſſued of that noble Blood which thy Anceſtors have owned; VVhat had my weak old age offended thee in, that thou couldſt not let my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation live, but muſt needs raviſh my Honour upon the brink of my Graved? Infamous Cheat, could'ſt thou chooſe no other way of being wicked to a dying Man, than in killing that Honour which alone ought to be Immortal? Go, thy ſenſual pleaſure has done me that wrong, which the loſs of thy Life cannot repair, and thy Death will rather be an Example to other perfidious Traitors, than a repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to me; away then, diſpatch him, cut his Throat, and pull out that deceiving Heart of his: No, ſtay, firſt call that mad and unfortunate Creature, that we may make a Marriage and a Burial of them both at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>Juſt as the old Man made an end of theſe words, a young Lady of incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Beauty, though much dejected and with tears in her Eyes, came into the Room; the ſight of her, and of thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible Charms which were her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35775:11"/>ſeparable Companions, did begin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the image of Death, which had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taken poſſeſſion of <hi>Don Diego's</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and to place ſome ſigns of joy and admiration in its room; when the Lady much more ſurpriz'd to find a Stranger, and an unknown Gentleman, in the hands of her Brothers and Father, could not chuſe but bluſh ſo extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that though it added a new luſtre to her Beauty, yet did it not a little puzzle her Relations, who expected a more ſteady conduct from her. Let us leave him a little in this perplexity, to eaſe the Reader of his, and tell him whence it proceeded.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman whoſe name was <hi>Don Frederick,</hi> who by all the advantages of Nature, Fortune, and Education, might juſtly challenge the title of very Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, had been long in love with <hi>Fenicia,</hi> the Lady whom we have deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; ſhe on her ſide, though her Beauty did every day adde ſome new conqueſt to her Empire, thought none worth owning and requiting but the happy <hi>Don Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick's</hi> addreſſes.</p>
               <p>Their intrigue was carried ſo cloſely, that their Parents of neither ſide were aware of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35775:11"/>it, and though <hi>Finicia's</hi> Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were very diligent in watching their Daughters actions, yet they found it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible at laſt to preſerve a thing, which the owner it ſelf endeavours every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to loſe; ſo that after a long per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, and the ſpecious ſhew of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate paſſion, <hi>Don Frederick</hi> obtained under a verbal promiſe of Marriage, thoſe favours which ſhould have followed that ſacred Union. As ſoon as <hi>Fenicia</hi> had thus put her Lover in poſſeſſion of that which was moſt precious to her, and that by the richneſs of thoſe hidden Treaſures, he had been repayed all the expence of tears and ſighs which he had been at, he let her ſee to her infinite grief, that he ſhould henceforth deſpiſe her as impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and plundered of her virtue. She ſoon perceived her errour by his coldneſs ere they parted, but his impatience to be gone not giving her time enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect entirely upon her fault, ſhe only ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his depart with a few Kiſſes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to come again to her at the ſame hour the following Night. In the mean time, conſidering with confuſion the greatneſs of her fault, and the probability
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35775:12"/>of <hi>Don Frederick's</hi> inconſtancy, ſhe ſaw no other remedy againſt that ſea of miſeries ready to break in upon her, than by oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to them the authority of her Father and Brothers: It was with much ado that ſhe brought her ſelf to this reſolution; and with more terrour that ſhe execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it.</p>
               <p>Upon this declaration the Father and Brothers were ſtruck with amazement, and inflamed with revenge; they knew the quality of <hi>Don Frederick,</hi> but had never ſeen his perſon; therefore ſeeing there was no other remedy, they projected to execute upon <hi>Don Frederick</hi> the following Night, all that which poor <hi>Don Diego</hi> in his room had already undergone, having been drawn in by his own curioſity, and <hi>Fenicia's</hi> inviting Voice; their deſign was to fright him into an accompliſhment of his word, or to waſh away the ſtain of their reputation with his blood; but to the end that he might not for ever after make their Siſter an object of ſorrow, by a cruel return of hard uſage, they reſolved that ſhe ſhould feign, that ſhe had reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing of their ſecret Loves, and ſhould in order of reſcuing him from their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35775:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>hands, affirm that they were miſtaken in the perſon, and that it was not he who had abuſed her credulity.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Fenicia</hi> ſeeing their real miſtake, was forced to lay aſide her deſigned arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and uſe ſincerity; Brothers, ſaid ſhe, you are in an errour, this Gentleman whom ye have thus ill treated, is not the Traytor <hi>Don Frederick:</hi> Oh Heavens! how great is my misfortune, firſt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my ſelf ſo far, then unluckily to have my ſhame, and that of my family, publiſhed before a Stranger! Her Brothers ſeemed to be amazed at her words, but ſtill ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them for counterfeit, could not chooſe but ſay to one another, look how rarely ſhe diſſembles, would not one ſwear ſhe ſaid true? She perceiving the double errour they were in, was forced to have recourſe to Oaths and Proteſtations, to free them from it, in ſo much that at laſt ſhe brought them to look with amazement upon one another, not knowing how to unriddle this myſterious intrigue. <hi>Don Diego</hi> on the other ſide did confirm all <hi>Fenicia's</hi> words, by telling of them his name, his quality, his profeſſion of a Church-man, incapable by conſequent of Marriage. The old
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35775:13"/>Man at laſt perceiving the miſtake they were in, fell into a great paſſion againſt his Daughter, as being the cauſe of all theſe unfortunate accidents, by her lewd proſtitution: Upon that <hi>Don Diego</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be a little at eaſe, hoping that now he ſhould be releaſed; but Fortune, who had reſolved to try his Courage, aſſaulted him afreſh, with the proſpect of a more deſperate danger. For <hi>Fenicia's</hi> Brothers angry at their errour, and perplexed to ſee the repute of their Family fallen into the hands and diſcretion of a Stranger, whom they had offended and ill treated, went aſide a little to think of a remedy in ſo great a diſtraction; and after a ſhort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, it was reſolved by them to lead him out of their Houſe, and in ſome by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place while it was yet dark, diſpatch him, for fear he ſhould reveal their infamy. In the mean time <hi>Lucifugne</hi> ſaid nothing, hoping ſtill that if he could once get out of that curſed houſe, either his feet or his hands ſhould protect him. Their deſign thus reſolved upon, was communicated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore execution to their old Father; but he being generous, and an enemy of bloody actions, roſe up, and coming to <hi>Don Diego</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35775:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>with a chearful countenance, Sir, ſaid he, I have a greater confidence in your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, than my Children have in the ſecurity of your death; I only deſire you to have compaſſion of an honourable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, whoſe ſhame has been lay'd open to you, and pray let our infamy be buried in the secret and ſilence of your generous Courage. This ſaid, he preſented him with his Sword again, reſtoring alſo his Guittar, then waiting upon him to the Street-door, offered to have him eſcorded whereſoever he pleaſed: <hi>Don Diego</hi> having thanked him, and reiterated his proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an eternal ſilence, as to what he had ſeen and heard, took his leaves; as ſoon as he was in the Street, and ſaw himſelf free from ſo imminent a danger, he made a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand vowes and reſolutions againſt all idle curioſities, all which he broke as eaſily as he made them. Having gone a part of his way home, and finding a great emotion in his ſpirits from the fright he had been in, he reſolved to ſettle them by the Art of Muſick; therefore taking his Guittar, he played and ſung to it.</p>
               <p>Juſt as he made an end of his Song, he found himſelf to be near his Lodging,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35775:14"/>and as he was going to open his door, a Perſon who had dogged him all the way from <hi>Fenicia's</hi> houſe, ſteps between him and it, and bids him ſtand; <hi>Don Diego</hi> a little ſurprized, gueſſed immediately that it might be one of her Brothers, who violating his Fathers Commands, was come to ſeek his revenge, or rather the aſſurance of his ſilence in his death; thereupon he goes back a little, and taking his Sword in his hand, though ſtill in his ſcabbard, comes up to him again to know his deſign; the Stranger without further delay, draws, and with ſome injurious words, provoking <hi>Don Diego</hi> to the like, was anſwered with as ſharp effects; for <hi>Diego</hi> after a little while, being very skilfull at his Weapon, made two ſuch home-thruſts upon the Stranger, that he fell, crying out, that he was a dead Man; after which he lay ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. <hi>Lucifugne</hi> who was as generous as valiant, having raiſed his Servants and got ſome Light, came to him, and finding by his adverſaries rich apparel, that he was a perſon of quality, had him taken up, and carried into that apartment which he alwayes reſerved for his Friends; there by the care that was taken of him, he came
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35775:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>to himſelf, and permitted his Wounds to be dreſſed; after which he told <hi>Don Diego,</hi> that his Name was <hi>Don Frederick,</hi> the ſame that had triumphed over the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent affections of <hi>Fenicia;</hi> that having been hindered by an important affair, from keeping exactly to the hour, appointed by her the Night before, he did come to the door juſt as <hi>Don Diego</hi> was let out; that the ſingularity of the Adventure having moved his curtoſity to know who it was, that did already ſhare with him in thoſe joyes of which he thought himſelf the only poſſeſſor, had prompted him to follow him to his Lodging, and that' there his impatient jealouſie had forced him to attaque him. <hi>Don Lucifugne</hi> having heard him out, very generouſly and franckly praiſed his courage and reſolution, but withall deſiring to clear all his ſuſpicions of <hi>Fenicia's</hi> chaſtity, related to him all his Adventure, and at the ſame time took an occaſion to preſs home to him the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the indignity he had offered an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Maid, who was only betrayed by the Love ſhe bare him; entreating him by the principles of Honour, which he profeſſed as a Gentleman, and thoſe of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35775:15"/>Conſcience, which he owned as a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and which in his preſent condition ought to be moſt prevalent, that he would do the injured Lady right, and free her deſolate Relations from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious reflection of their Daughters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy. <hi>Don Frederick</hi> was moved by his reaſons, and his own Conſcience, and ſending for a Prieſt, declared in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and before all the Company, that he would accompliſh his prormiſe of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to <hi>Fenicia,</hi> as ſoon as by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery he ſhould be in a condition to do it.</p>
               <p>His juſt Vow was receiv'd and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of in Heaven, and from that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment his wounds began to mend; ſo in a few dayes, he was in a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requiſite for the accompliſhment of his deſign; to this end, he entreated: <hi>Don Diego,</hi> with whom he had contracted a moſt intimate friendſhip, to go and viſit <hi>Fenicia</hi> from him, and to give her theſe new aſſurances of his fidelity; entreating him withall, not to ſpeak of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, for fear frighting her: She all this while, poor Lady, was infinitely afflicted, not hearing any news at all of <hi>Don Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35775:15"/>in ſo much that the grief of her mind, prevailing upon her body, had brought her to keep her bed in a moſt languiſhing condition. In the mean time, her four Brothers raging for the affront put upon their Family, and having in vain ſought the Author of it in <hi>Madrid,</hi> thought he had abſented himſelf, and thereupon dividing, every one had took a different way to find him out, and take a bloody vengeance of this Murderer of their Siſters Honour.</p>
               <p>One day as <hi>Fenicia</hi> and her deſolate Father were talking of their misfortunes, which they did begin to think beyond a remedy, <hi>Don Diego</hi> came in to viſit them; we need not ask if they were ſurprized at his ſight, being not able to gueſs at the occaſion of his coming to them; but <hi>Lucifugne</hi> unwilling to keep them long in expectation of ſuch joyfull tidings, gave them ſo many aſſurances of the truth of what he ſaid, that <hi>Fenicia</hi> and her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were like to have found their joy as fatal to them as their grief, ſo great was the tranſport they were in; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Diego</hi> like an Angel from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven giving him a thouſand thanks for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35775:16"/>his generous proceeding towards them; <hi>Fenicia</hi> ſoon recovered her decayed Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and her Lover being perfectly cured, came himſelf with <hi>Don Diego</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the reality of his intentions; there now remained nothing to compleat their joy, but the preſence of the four Brothers; meſſengers were diſpatched to them on all hands, who having luckily found them out, made them haſte to ſee the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of their Family: <hi>Don Fredericks</hi> Friends were all invited to the Wedding, which was kept with great Solemnity, and amongſt all the Aſſembly, <hi>Don Diego Lucifugne</hi> was the Perſon moſt reſpected and Honourable, as having been the main inſtrument of bringing all the intrigue to end in ſo happy a ſucceſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35775:16"/>
               <head>Adventure the ſecond.</head>
               <p>THe memory of theſe paſt accidents, might have been the Subject of a very profitable Meditation for <hi>Don Diego,</hi> if he had pleaſed; but it being a very hard matter to regulate the inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate motions of a wilde Nature, by any conſideration whatſoever, that of ſo imminent a danger avoided was not powerfull enough to make him refrain from is extravagant Night-Exerciſes. He had with him a Friend, whoſe name was <hi>Almen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor,</hi> one who had loved him from his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der years, for the vivacity of his Wit, and the generouſneſs of his Courage, but who was much againſt the irregular courſe of his life, and could not but with grief ſee thoſe ſeeds of virtue choaked in debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, which elſe would have bore ſuch fair fruit of true Honour: He had often endeavoured by his perſwaſions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this rebellious Nature, to ſubmit to the Laws of prudence and moderation, and now thinking this a very fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſtrike the nail home to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35775:17"/>head, he came to him, and very ſeriouſly harangu'd him in this manner.</p>
               <p>I ſhould never have thought, Sir, that you could have been ſo unjuſt to me, and ſo cruel to your ſelf, as to my great grief I now find you are: Muſt all the years and pains which I have ſpent in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to poliſh your mind, and elevate your Soul, be not only loſt, but rewarded with that ſhame and reproach which cannot but reflect upon me, from the perverſity of your converſation? And muſt I, that alwayes reckoned to reap in the applauſe given to your virtues, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of my pains, be now fruſtrated of all my deſigns? Sure you cannot be ſo ill natur'd, or if my intereſt alone can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not move you, adde your own to the ballance, and ſee if it will not then weigh down all the fondneſs of youthly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: are you that have ſo much wit, not endowed with judgement enough to diſtinguiſh between the lightneſs of your Camerades applauſe, and the ſolid value of the graver ſort of Men? But ſetting all that aſide, is not the health of your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the welfare of your Soul, nay your Life it ſelf endangered every moment in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35775:17"/>theſe bizarr ſallies, which you make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in the dark? you have but lately eſcaped a moſt prodigious danger, and yet cannot this prevail with you to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear a courſe of Life, which muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be very fatal both to your Life and Honour, one of theſe Nights; What I ſay, <hi>Seignor Don Diego,</hi> is out of pure af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to you, and to ſhew you the little ſelf-love I am guided by; I have hitherto enjoyed the benefit of your For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but if I ſhould continue ſo to do, I ſhould think my ſelf little leſs than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to your Misfortunes; I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by your leave retire, and rather feed upon the Bread of labour and induſtry, than that of ſorrow, which I muſt expect if I ſtay with you. Theſe words of <hi>Almanzor,</hi> were accompanied with a like action, for ſteping towards the door, he made as if he would have gone away; but <hi>Don Diego</hi> getting hold of him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him not to forſake him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to endeavour an amendment; and to begin, he pull'd off his Sword, and layd it by, and for two whole dayes lived a very regular life, that is, making ufe of the Night and the Day according to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35775:18"/>their Natural inſtitution: But his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being all this while violented, upon the third Evening he began to deteſt <hi>Almanzors</hi> ſeverity, and calling him pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantick Tyrant of his Natural liberty, was reſolv'd to ſhake off the Fetters of his imperious Councels; when he heard the noiſe of a Coach in the Street, it being a by-place, was ſeldom troubled with this ſort of noiſe, which made <hi>Don Diego</hi> the more attentive to its motions: It ſtopped a little ſhort of his Window, and preſently a Voice, which ſeemed to be that of a Woman, Sung divinely well to a Lute, which ſhe touched as harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly; but the ſweetneſs of her Muſick, could not abate the ſharpneſs of her Song, which was ſo ſatyrical and biting upon a Lady of pleaſure that lived hard by the Houſe, and as it were under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of our <hi>Adventurer,</hi> that he had ſcarce the patience to hear it out; He got on his Doublet and Breeches, and taking his Sword in his hand, run down as faſt as he could; the Coach was gone before he came into the Street, and all that he could do, was by following it at a diſtance, to obſerve the Houſe it went into.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35775:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>But to avoid confuſion, let us give theſe Ladies their Names, and relate their Adventure. She whom <hi>Don Diego</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, was called <hi>Carcelia,</hi> and the other who had thus provoked her, went by the name of <hi>Fauſtina,</hi> both of quality and life ſo like, that the praiſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe of the one, might without injury be adopted to the other: whereupon <hi>Don Diego</hi> having got a copy of thoſe verſes, tranſpos'd their names, and found that the attributes did ſtill ſute; wherefore he firſt reſolved to have them ſung over again at <hi>Fauſtinaes</hi> Window; but that being but a ſimple retaliation, he accompanied it with the interludes of a new inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was thus contrived and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> invited to Supper one Night, five or ſix of the wildeſt young Men of his acquaintance, and having in the middle of their Mirth, layed open to them his reſolution of being revenged upon <hi>Fauſtina,</hi> asked their opinion: They all anſwered to the affirmative, and one propoſing one thing, another another, at laſt theſe Articles were reſolved upon.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35775:19"/>
                  <item>1. That there ſhould be a Serenade given, with all ſorts of ridiculous Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>viz.</hi> two Sow-gelders Horns, two broken Bells, two Guittars, and two Viols out of Tune, and four Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of a different bigneſs.</item>
                  <item>2. That there ſhould be compoſed a Dialogue in Verſe, to be recited by two young Men of the company, whereof one ſhould repreſent <hi>Fauſtina,</hi> and the other <hi>Popaa</hi> her Siſter; that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Dialogue ſhould be ſome quarreling expoſtulations between the two Siſters, which ſhould divulge the infamy of their life and profeſſion.</item>
                  <item>3. That <hi>Don Diego</hi> ſhould prepare a kind of triumphal Chariot, which ſhould be attended with a good number of lighted Torches, and that the ſaid Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot ſhould be the Stage of their action; that it ſhould ſtop juſt before <hi>Fauſtinaes</hi> Window, which ſhould be opened by force, if ſhe did not do it voluntarily.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This being reſolv'd <hi>nemine contradicente,</hi> the beſt Poet was charged with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Dialogue; and when it came to be learned by Heart, there were a great many meeting Dinners, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35775:19"/>Collations at <hi>Don Diego's,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Actors, and perfect them in their parts; and at laſt, the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was acted, <hi>Carcelia</hi> was invited to give her cenſure, and ſee what was to be added to, or taken away from this impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent piece of revenge. This laſt repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion having very much pleaſed all the company, it was decreed, that it ſhould be acted for good and all the following Night, for fear leaſt it might take vent, and be countermined by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of the concerned parties, who could in a need muſter good Auxiliaries among the young Gallants of the Town.</p>
               <p>Midnight being come, they ſet forth in great State from <hi>Don Diego's</hi> Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, having in a readineſs all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for their moſt infernal Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nade, yet not touching on them till they ſhould come to <hi>Fauſtinaes</hi> Street, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to wake no body, but thoſe who ſhould be ſo unlucky as to have ſo ill Neighbours as theſe two Siſters were: The Chariot beginning to move, in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn dump, in the ſilence of the Night, and being environ'd round with Torches, its ſelf filled with antick Perſons, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35775:20"/>followed by others in a Maſcarade dreſs, might have been a ſpectacle worthy the loſs of ſome ſleep. It got at laſt, with much ado, being drawn by 8. Courſiers called Porters, to the entrance of <hi>Fauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naes</hi> Street, where they had ſubject to think all their labour loſt, for the paſſage was ſtrongly barricadoed; the buſineſs was, that a perſon of very great Quality being fallen ſick in it, had obtain'd leave of the Magiſtrate, to plant ſome poſts acroſs the Street, to hinder Coaches and Carts from paſſing and interrupting that little reſt which his diſtemper would allow him to take. <hi>Don Lucifugne</hi> having called a Council, it was reſolved not to go back, but to force through this obſtacle: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the poſts were attaqu'd, and in a trice thrown down, every one having put to a helping hand; the breach being wide enough, the Machine entered, and being come under <hi>Fauſtinaes</hi> Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, firſt gave her a Salve of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renade, to prepare her attention to the reſt; but this ſo Diabolick a noiſe, having put all the ſick Lords houſe in an uproar, out came his Maſter of the Horſe, to know what the matter was, and to deſire them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35775:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be gone; <hi>Don Diego</hi> met him, and with good words having a little quieted him, promiſing to withdraw, as ſoon as he had turned his back, commanded the Dialogue to be begun; but by this time the Lords family had by his Command taken Arms, and the Coachmen, Grooms, Cooks, and Scullions, iſſued out with their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Weapons, Pitch-forks, Spits, Tonges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſeeing that Chariot there ſtill, came furiouſly on to overthrow it and the Actors; but on the other ſide, <hi>Don Diego</hi> and his Camerades, with Link<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys and Porters interpoſing, there began a fray, in which many a head was broke, as well as the Peace, on each ſide; and at laſt, after a pretty ſmart conflict, each party well ſatisfied with their bang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, retired, carrying off their wounded Friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fauſtina</hi> and <hi>Popaea,</hi> who were come to their Windows, and had perceived that all this tintamarr was for them, had an exceeding joy to ſee it diſappointed, with an addition of revenge upon the Actors which they could never have hoped for; but their tranſports were ſoon at an end, for the next day the Lord their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35775:21"/>being informed, that they were the cauſe of theſe Night ſcandals, cauſed them to be baniſhed <hi>Madrid:</hi> Some of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batants on each ſide were clapt up, and came off for ſmall fines; <hi>Don Diego</hi> for his part, got clear of the Lords purſuit, by pleading his priviledge of being judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an Eccleſiaſtical Court, having alſo found favour in the Kings; for bating his Nocturn Extravagancies, he was a Man of moſt excellent Convenſation, and very VVitty Company.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:35775:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Adventure the third.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almanzor</hi> weary of <hi>Don Diego's</hi> extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies, and almoſt out of Charity with himſelf, for his indulgency in enduring them, ſeeing him at laſt delivered from the purſuit of the Law, and all its evil conſequences, reſolved alſo to free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from all the terrours and fears he was continually in, for his Friends ſafety: VVhereupon he told <hi>Don Diego,</hi> that the greateſt part of the blame of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate life, lighting upon him, as one who had the greateſt ſhare in his educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he could do no leſs than let the World ſee by his retreat, that he did entirely diſſent from all vicious courſes, and that not being able to hinder them, he was at leaſt reſolved not to countenance them any longer. <hi>Don Diego</hi> having heard him out, anſwered very fairly, that he was ſorry things were come to that pitch, as to neceſſitate a Rupture between them, but that ſince his life was of ſo little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to his Friends inclinations, it was beſt for them both to ſeparate: <hi>Almanzor</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:35775:22"/>was a little ſurprized to ſee himſelf taken at his word, for it was not his intention to withdraw; but did only hope by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere reiteration of his admonitions, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations to leave <hi>Don Diego,</hi> ſo to perplex him, as either to better his own condition in ſtaying, or make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to live more regularly: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, being thus anſwered, he thought he could do no leſs for his honour, than effectuate his parole, which accordingly he did, and retired into a private Lodging in the Town; but at the end of a few dayes, he found that his huffing, coſt him pretty dear; for having never before had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the trouble of living at his own charges, he ſoon began to compare it with the pleaſure of living coſt-free upon anothers purſe, and found a vaſt difference between thoſe two things; but the value of things is never ſo well underſtood, as when the enjoyment of them is paſt: being weary of the inconveniencies of his new life, he got ſome perſons of Quality to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe towards <hi>Don Diego,</hi> and to mediate his return to him; they found him well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, in regard of their ancient friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; but to put an invincible obſtacle to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35775:22"/>all future fallings out, <hi>Don Diego</hi> faſtned theſe Articles upon the favour of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admittance.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That all authority of a Governour ſhould be ſuppreſſed.</item>
                  <item>2. That each of them ſhould live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own fancy, taking no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of one anothers comportments.</item>
                  <item>3. That for the better execution of this agreement, <hi>Almanzor</hi> ſhould live in that apartment which <hi>Don Diego</hi> did uſe to keep for his Friends.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This was accordingly executed, and <hi>Don Diego</hi> vexy well pleaſed to ſee, that he had at laſt ſhaken off the yoke of <hi>Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zors</hi> pedantick juriſdiction; the natural diſpoſition which <hi>Don Diego</hi> had to play upon divers inſtruments, and ſing to them, being followed with ſo great an excellency in that Art, that moſt Maſters did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire him, made him very inquiſitive af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all that excelled that way; ſo that at laſt he came to hear of a young Lady, who was ſaid to have attained ſo great a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the ſame thing, that ſhe was talked of by all <hi>Madrid</hi> for her skill, both in Compoſing, Playing, and Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This was a great incitement to our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35775:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Adventurer to be acquainted with her; but her Beauty, which was more Charming, having at the firſt ſight he had of her' made deeper impreſſions in his Soul, he never gave over till he got an opportunity of ſeeing her at a Kinſwomans houſe; there he omitted no ſort of Courtſhip to win her inclinations, but could not bring her to any greater condeſcendencies, than ſuch civilities and modeſt favours as might have been granted to indifferent Perſons.</p>
               <p>The Ladies Name was <hi>Sirena,</hi> and ſhe was Married to a perſon of quality, but prodigiouſly jealous of her; a great jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which he had made towards the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt parts of <hi>Spain,</hi> had given <hi>Don Diego</hi> all theſe opportunities of making his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and it may be inſpired the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy too with more reſiſtance, than the tyrannical conduct of a jealous Husband would have let her uſe at another time; for 'tis a moſt certain rule, that reſtraint in Ladies encreaſes the deſire of liberty, which once obtain'd or freely given, is more moderately made uſe of. The Husband being at laſt come home, and a greater reſtraint put upon <hi>Sirenas</hi> liberty, ſhe gave <hi>Don Diego</hi> notice of it, deſiring
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35775:23"/>him to forbear to give any publick ſigns of his paſſion, for fear her Husband ſhould be alarmed by them; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, appointed him a Rendezvous the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Night, at the ſame Kinſwomans houſe, and that he ſhould meet with a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before the door, who ſhould introduce: <hi>Don Diego</hi> received this Meſſage with an unexpreſſible joy, hoping that now he had at laſt attain'd to the top of all his wiſhies, ſince <hi>Sirena</hi> upon her own move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did take care of the continuation of their Amours: The hour came, he dreſſed himſelf to his beſt advantage, and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſides good Arms againſt all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky accidents, he ſet forth with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſire not to be the laſt at the place of aſſignation. Being come to the Houſe, he found no body walking there to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, whereupon ſuppoſing that his Amorous impatience might have made him be too diligent, he ſtayed in a ſhop hard by; after a delay of an hour, and juſt as he begun to loſe patience, a Maid of <hi>Sirena's</hi> beckon'd to him from the door, to go a little farther off from the Houſe; She then following him, told him, that her Miſtreſs was gone to take the Air with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35775:24"/>her Maſter, in ſome Garden about the Town, but that ſhe would hardly ſtay above two hours, at the end of which he might return, and be ſure to meet her: This diſappointment, though very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, was a little ſweetned by the hopes of having a greater liberty of enjoying <hi>Sirena,</hi> when ſhe ſhould be rid of her fond old Husband, to whoſe freſh arrival, he judged, ſhe had been forc'd to ſacrifice ſome of thoſe moments, which ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for him. The better to divert his unquiet impatience, till the happy hour ſhould come, he reſolv'd to take a turn in the Prado of <hi>Madrid,</hi> the place where the Coaches take the Air; the evening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat cold, and the Skie a little overcaſt, had driven the Coaches and all the Company away betimes; ſo that though it were not much paſt ten a clock when <hi>Don Diego</hi> came thither, he found as great a ſolitude in the Prado, as if it had been ſome remote Deſart: he walked twice from one end to the other, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining at liberty the variety of his thoughts, till he thought it was almoſt time to go back to his aſſignation; but juſt as he was going out at one end, he heard
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35775:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>not far off the moaning voice of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and eaſily diſtinguiſh'd theſe words; Is it poſſible, dear Husband, that ſo trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous a deſign can come into your mind, as to reſolve to kill one, who loves you ſo dearly? and have you brought me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only to murder me ſo barbarouſly? <hi>Don Diego</hi> mov'd with compaſſion, went immediately towards the place whence the voice proceeded, deſirous to deliver a Perſon brought to ſo great a diſtreſs: he had not gone twenty ſteps, but he found a Coach drawn by two Horſes, cloſe ſhut on one ſide, and open on the other; and a little further, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd a Man on foot, with his Sword drawn in his hand, and a Lady upon her knees before him. The Man hearing ſome body draw near, came towards <hi>Don Diego,</hi> and bid him ſtand; ſtand thy ſelf, replyed our Adventurer, and know that I come hither to puniſh thee, for thy bloody attempt upon that poor Ladies life, whoſe tears I ſee cannot ſoften thy hard and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Breaſt. At this the other ſeeing himſelf offended in his honour, made no other repartie but with his Sword; <hi>Don Diego</hi> parr'd the thruſt, and being very
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35775:25"/>adroit, gave him two wounds, one upon the other, inſomuch that he fell, crying, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> I am dead: At this deadly cry the Lady fell into a ſwoun; <hi>Don Diego</hi> haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to her, found her lying upon the ground without ſence or motion; he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently took her in his arms, and having put her into the Coach, and faſtned cloſe the boot, he got up into the box, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Coach-man, and drave ſtraight to his own Lodging; he ſoon knock'd up <hi>Almanzor,</hi> and making him come out without any light, for fear of making his Neighbours ſpectators of what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to conceal, they two carryed in the Lady, who was not yet come to her ſelf: Then he told <hi>Almanzor</hi> ſuccinctly, that ſhe was a Lady that he did not know; that he had reſcu'd her from a barbarous Husband, who was going to attempt upon her life; that he deſired him to have a ſingular care of her, till he ſhould return, being now forc'd to go out again upon urgent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: This ſaid, he departed, and getting up again upon the Coach-box, he drave till he came before the Windows of a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who had a great reputation of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Charity; him he called by his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35775:25"/>Name, and having obliged him to look out, told him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the Coach he then was upon, was a ſtray Coach which he had met with in the Street, without any body to own or drive it; and that he thought it could not be diſpoſed into better hands than his, whoſe Charity he knew would be ſolicitous to diſcover the right owner, and reſtore it to him: Thus ſaid, he leaped off the box, and ran away as faſt as he could: he took his way towards <hi>Sirenas</hi> houſe, much perplexed with himſelf, and concluding that he had let ſlip, the time of his aſſignation; but when he came near, he met the Maid, who told him that her Miſtreſs was not yet come home; and that ſhe believed that ſhe and her Husband were gone to ſee her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was a very rich Widdow, whom they both courted, as expecting to be well remembred in her Will; that if it were ſo, it would be in vain to expect het home that Night: This long diſcourſe caſt ſome ſuſpicious thoughts into <hi>Don Diego's</hi> breaſt, that the Maid was not ſo true to him as he could wiſh, taking all this ſtory for an invented lye; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſirous to be better informed, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35775:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>not to ſtir very far from <hi>Sirenaes</hi> houſe, till towards Morning; he walked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a little, and having been abſent about a quarter of an hour, came back, and was not a little aſtoniſhed to ſee lights at almoſt all the windows, and to find <hi>Sirenaes</hi> houſe full of Serjeants, and other Officers of Juſtice, with a great multitude of People; he draws near, and having enquired of ſome body what the matter was, was told, that <hi>Don Leander, Sirenaes</hi> Husband, was brought home wounded, and that it was yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known how and by whom ſo unlucky an accident had befallen him; <hi>Don Diego</hi> upon this withdrew, judging well that if he ſhould betaken notice of, as one that had courted <hi>Leanders</hi> VVife, and be found beſides with; Fire-arms about him, he might be laid hold of upon ſuſpicion, which would bring him into a great deal of trouble, though according to his own o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, he thought himſelf far from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a hand in the matter.</p>
               <p>But now let us return to <hi>Sirena,</hi> whom we had left in <hi>Almanzors</hi> hands; he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lighted a Candle, and poured ſome drops of a Cordial down the Ladies throat, had with much ado brought her
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35775:26"/>to her ſelf again: as ſoon as ſhe opened her eyes, ſhe was ſtrangely ſurprized to finde her ſelf in an unknown place, in the power of a Stranger; but ſtill ſuppoſing that he was the Man who had preſerved her from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing killed: Sir, ſaid ſhe, having already the obligation of my life to your valour, I cannot expect leſſe than the preſervation of my honour from your generoſity, and therefore without informing your ſelf far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who I am, I deſire you to cauſe me to be led to <hi>St. Jeroms</hi> Church door, and there to be left to my own liberty; alas, the Gentleman you killed was my Husband, and though he was even then preparing to make me breath my laſt, yet can I not but be concerned at his misfortune, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan my deſtiny, which could find no other way to deliver my innocency from his bloody attempt.</p>
               <p>The aſtoniſhment of <hi>Almanzor,</hi> was not inferiour to the ſurprize of the fair Lady; but judging immediately that <hi>Don Diego</hi> was he who had killed her Husband, he thought fit by all means to conceal from her the Author of her misfortunes; and thereupon anſwering the Lady with great civility, told her, that her requeſt ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35775:27"/>be granted, provided ſhe would conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to one of his, which was, to give him leave to blind her eyes with a handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and promiſe not to go about to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind her ſelf, till he ſhould leave her to her ſelf before <hi>St Jeroms</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>The Lady ſeeing her ſelf at his mercy, was forced to rely upon his diſcretion, and give her ſelf up to his conduct; immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <hi>Almanzor</hi> made a <hi>Cupid</hi> of this <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and taking her by the hand, led her out of the Houſe; at every ſtep he made, he would look behind him, imagining ſtill that the Officers of Juſtice were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſeiſe upon him: In theſe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions he came before <hi>St. Jeroms</hi> Convent, there taking leave of her, he ran away as faſt as his legs would carry him, thinking himſelf very happy when once he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered <hi>Don Diego's</hi> houſe. The Lady perceiving her ſelf at liberty, unblinded her eyes, and finding her ſelf before <hi>St. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roms</hi> Convent, took her refuge in her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, which was hard by.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> in the mean time came home, almoſt as ſoon as <hi>Almanzor,</hi> and finding him quite out of breath, and ſcare able to ſpeak, by reaſon of his haſty courſe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35775:27"/>he could not chooſe but ask him the cauſe of the great alteration he ſaw in him; the cauſe, anſwered <hi>Almanzor</hi> grumbling, is your inconſiderate and raſh conduct, which brings all thoſe which concern themſelves for your Life and Honour, into eternal perplexities: Thereupon he told him all that had paſſed between himſelf and the Lady, and how he had conveyed her away with her eyes blinded, for fear ſhe ſhould know the place ſhe had been in, and by conſequent her Husbands murtherer, whom ſhe might, it may be, in a fit of vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, accuſe before the Judges, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the reputation of an Heroick courage, in loving her Husband ſo far, as to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him for killing him, even one that had ſaved her own life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> could not chooſe but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his Friends prudence, in the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of this ſo tickliſh a buſineſs, and gave him a thouſand thanks, and as many em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces for his friendly proceeding; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this he related to him his love for <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena,</hi> and how he had been diſappointed of his aſſignation. <hi>Almanzor</hi> gave him prudent advice to deſiſt from his paſſion, leſt it might bring him into ſome incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35775:28"/>worſe than any he had hitherto undergone; after this, it being almoſt day, they both retired and went to ſleep.</p>
               <p>They had not reſted above two hours, when they were both awakned by a very loud knocking at the Street door; at firſt, the deſire they had to enjoy ſome repoſe, made them neglect the noiſe, but it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling, cauſed <hi>Don Diego</hi> at laſt to riſe, thinking it might be ſome Officers who had made a diſcovery of the laſt Nights Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures; but coming to the door, he found it was no body but a Boy, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him with a Letter from <hi>Sirena;</hi> the ſound of that pleaſing Name, infuſed tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility into his troubled Spirits: he made the Meſſenger come in, and opening his Letter, found it contained theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35775:28"/>
                     <head>The Letter of <hi>Sirena,</hi> to <hi>Don Diego.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DOn Leander</hi> my Husband, continually rack'd by his own jealous diſpoſition, but afreſh tormented by the perfidious tales of my diſloyal waiting-Woman, did laſt Night plot a moſt horrid deſign againſt my life; he deſired me to go out with him to take the Air, to which I having condeſcended, he told me there was a Coach ſtayed for us at the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Street; he having ſo ordered it, that he might avoid taking with him ſome Ladies of the Neighbour-hood, who would have expected that civility from him, if they had ſeen the Coach before our door; we fetched ſo great a compaſs in the Town, that it was very late when we came to the Prado, where we found no Body, the Company being all retired; he deſired me to take one turn with him, and as ſoon as we were lighted, he told me he would give me the diverſion of hearing one of his Friends Pages ſing, and thereupon commanded the Coachman to go to ſuch a place and fetch him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As ſoon as we were alone, <hi>Don Leander</hi> with a threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning voice, began to reproach me with all
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35775:29"/>thoſe imaginary injuries which he fancied I had done him, and without giving me any leiſure or time to juſtifie my ſelf, pronounced the cruel ſentence of my Death, of which he made himſelf both Judge and Executor: I ſeeing his bloody reſolution, endeavoured by my tears and ſupplications to mollifie his hard Heart; but all in vain, if Heaven, which protects innocency, had not raiſed me up a defenſour; one who appeared before us of a ſudden, and who with great valour in an inſtant overcame my perfidious Husband, and left him dead upon the place; his fall and deadly outcry, joyned with the fright I was in before, ſo prevailed upon my Spirits, that they left me, and I fell into a ſwoun; as ſoon as I came to my ſelf again, I ſound my ſelf in an unknown houſe, and in the hands of a ſtranger, one of a different profeſſion from that of armes: I intreated him to convey me to the door of <hi>St. Jeroms</hi> Church, which he did, having firſt blinded me, without giving me any reaſon for his procedure; as ſoon as I was at the place I had deſired, he left me, and vaniſhed away ſo ſuddenly, that I could not diſcern which way he took. I firſt retired to my mothers, and from thence to a Religions houſe, which this bearer will Name to you. I expect
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35775:29"/>your Councel and aſſiſtance, as being one who is much a Gentleman, and a Friend to the diſtreſſed</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Sirena.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>At every period of this Letter, <hi>Don Diego,</hi> and <hi>Almanzor</hi> who had likewiſe riſe and was come to him, could not chooſe but look upon one another, and ſtand aſtoniſhed like two ſtatues, to ſee the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity of the Adventure. <hi>Don Diego</hi> on his ſide was inconſolable, when he reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he had had in his power the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all his wiſhes, without being able to make uſe of ſo lucky an occaſion; and did begin to deteſt <hi>Almanzors</hi> timorous conduct, which had deprived him of the joyes of his life. But thoſe Chymerical reflections, were interrupted by the wiſer conſideration of <hi>Almanzor,</hi> who made it appear, that <hi>Sirenas</hi> ſtaying with them, muſt needs have ended in ſome tragical event for them all; that therefore the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentation of ſuch company was dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and abſolutely to be laid aſide; that however, he did not diſapprove of a viſit to the diſtreſſed Lady, now ſhe was in the Monaſtery; but leſt all this ſhould be a trap laid by the waiting VVoman, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35775:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>the author of <hi>Leanders</hi> murther, he offered to go firſt and diſcover what reality there was in the buſineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> was ruled by him for this once, and <hi>Almanzor</hi> finding <hi>Sirenas</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation true, and her Perſon in the Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery, came and fetched <hi>Don Diego</hi> to her: there they had a great conference, and diſcovered to one another all the circumſtances of the action, by which <hi>Sirena</hi> found her ſelf obliged to <hi>Don Diego</hi> for her life; ſhe thanked him, and promiſed not to bring him into any trouble upon her Husbands account.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leander</hi> in the mean time, was in the hands of the Officers of Juſtice, and of the Chirurgions, in unexpreſſible torments of minde and body; he had voluntarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the intended murther of his Wife, and was therefore a Priſoner till it ſhould be known what was become of her: every body that heard of the ſtory, was paſſionate to know the name of the Gentleman, that had ſo couragiouſly reſcued and preſerv'd <hi>Sirena;</hi> but <hi>Don Lucifugne</hi> rather choſe to loſe the fruit of his valour, for fear leſt the ſweetneſs of the glory of it, ſhould be ſpoil'd by the bitterneſs of the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35775:30"/>of the Law; a little after the news of <hi>Leanders</hi> death was brought to him, he having rather died of the torment of his mind, and thoſe wounds which his raſh conduct had inflicted upon his own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, than of thoſe which <hi>Don Diego</hi> had given his Body. <hi>Sirena</hi> afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his loſs, forſook the World, and turned Nun, reſolving to do penance for all the errours of her life. <hi>Don Diego</hi> ſtruck with an extream diſpleaſure at the news of it, fell ſick, and had almoſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Leander</hi> to the other VVorld.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <head>Adventure the fourth.</head>
               <p>LOng was <hi>Don Diego's</hi> ſickneſs, but the tediouſneſs of it was much eaſed, by the continual aſſiſtance of <hi>Almanzor;</hi> for he did not only endeavour himſelf to divert his Friend with pleaſing diſcourſes, but did alſo procure him many viſits from divers others, who were better acquainted with the news of the Town and Court: by theſe helps he got upon his Legs again,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35775:31"/>and by his carriage at firſt, let every body preſume that he was as well cured of the ill cuſtoms of his mind, as of the bad ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of his Body; for during ſome dayes, he payed and received viſits in the day time: but the Carnaval, which is a ſeaſon of Debauch, being come, he preſently fell into his old extravagancies, declaring a new VVar againſt day-light, and making a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn league with the hours of the Night. Upon the evening of <hi>Shrove-tueſday,</hi> he was invited by ſome of his Friends to a great Supper, to take their leave of Fleſh; the Supper done, finding that the Company inſtead of diverting themſelves with ſome ingenious frolick, were fallen to drinking, and to ſlandering their Neighbours, he ſtole ſecretly away, with a deſign to go to another aſſembly, where he knew there would be more innocent mirth: he had ſcarce gone half the way he intended, when he found himſelf before the great Gate of a Houſe, which was wide open; his curioſity would not let him go by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out going in. He takes his Sword in his hand, and entring by the Gate, went through a long dark Ally, which brought him into a great wide open place, where he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35775:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>could ſee nothing neither; this ſtop'd him a while, and made him reflect, that it might be great temerity to go on; yet thinking it Cowardice to go back, he grop'd along the Walls, till he found a door half open, which as he endeavoured to thruſt wider open, he fell into a trap, which made him tumble headlong into a place fourteen or fifteen foot under ground, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving as good luck would have it, no other miſchief in his fall, than the loſs of his Sword, which he had been forc'd to let go to endeavour to catch hold of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſave himſelf: At the ſame time he heard a Voice, which ſeemed to come from a remote place, which asked, Who goes there? <hi>Don Diego</hi> a little ſtun'd with his fall, was not ſo ready to anſwer, but that the Voice redoubled again in a threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning tone, <hi>Who goes there?</hi> our Adventurer being afraid leſt ſome body ſhould attaque him, to his great diſadvantage, before he had found his Sword, which he was groping for, was forc'd to ſay, 'tis a Man all alone: If it be a Man, anſwered the Volce, let him come in hither. At theſe words, <hi>Don Lucifugne</hi> began to reſent his bold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; but there being no going back, he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35775:32"/>drew near to a door, through which there came a little glimmering or light; as ſoon as he paſſed it, he came into a great Hall, at the four corners of which were hung four lamps, which yielded ſo weak and pale a light, that they did but juſt aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the native horrour of the place; he goes on, and at one end perceives the figures of two Men, all in deep mourning, each of them ſitting in a great elbow Chair, the one leaning upon his hand, as if he had been aſleep, and the other wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; they both ſeem'd to attend a dead Body, which lay ſtretched at their feet, and wraped up in a winding-ſheet.</p>
               <p>At this moſt horrid ſight, <hi>Don Diego</hi> was a little mov'd with fear, when on a ſudden, the ſleeping Man ſtarting up, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan joyntly with the other to put theſe queſtions to our Adventurer. Art not thou the Man whom the VVorld calls <hi>Seignor Don Diego?</hi> Yes, replyed he, trembling, but how came you by my Name? Trouble not thy ſelf about that, replyed the Voices conjoyntly, but only anſwer to our interrogations, for upon thy anſwer depend many things which we have to do this Night. At theſe words
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35775:32"/>he would fain have been ſomewhere elſe, but there being no remedy, he replyed boldly, I am <hi>Don Diego;</hi> and what are you, Devils? I believe he knows us, ſays one to the other; he will the better obey our Commands, replyed the other: firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued they, thou muſt ſtay here and keep this body, while we go to execute the Commands of a Superiour Power; ſtir not from hence, as thou tendereſt thy ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Immediately, without ſlaying for his anſwer, they roſe up, and going out at the door, ſhut it after them upon our Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer. <hi>Don Diego</hi> ſeeing himſelf left alone with a dead Man, began to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend himſelf to the protection of God Almighty, and all his Saints, covering himſelf with ſigns of the Croſs from top to toe.</p>
               <p>The two Mourners had not been gone above a quarter of an hour, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to hear horrid groanes, and the noiſe of iron Chains, with ſuch rumbling as if the Houſe had been falling down; this having produced in him a ſtrange terrour, he went towards the door, with a deſign to get out, if poſſible; but as he was almoſt at it, he heard a fearfull Voice behind him,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35775:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>which in a ſad tone cried to him, ſtay <hi>Don Diego,</hi> do not think to flie from me; thou haſt not yet leave to depart, come back, or I'le follow thee. At theſe words, looking back, he perceiv'd the dead Man a riſing up, and found that the Voice came from him; who continued thus, Know that I am he whom thou didſt deprive of this life a few daies ago, without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received any injury from me: Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Man, canſt thou hope to avoid the vengeance of Heaven? 'tis by its order that thou art brought hither to hear my juſt complaints, draw near therefore, that I may reproach thee with all thy crimes.</p>
               <p>This diſcourſe put <hi>Don Diego</hi> into a mortal Trance; he certainly believed, that it was the Ghoſt of dead <hi>Leander,</hi> come from another World to torment him; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs he drew nearer, not daring to do otherwiſe, and the dead Man purſued thus. I muſt confeſs, that thou didſt kill me in the Field, and fighting bravely with me; but becauſe I had not learned in my Youth to fence, thou hadſt an eaſie victory over me; but now thou ſhalt do me reaſon, come let us wraſtle, body to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35775:33"/>upon condition, that if thou doſt give me a fair fall, my death ſhall be forgiven thee, and neither I nor any of my Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades ſhall ever diſquiet thee more. But if I overcome thee, thou ſhalt be bound to come every Year, upon the day of my death, and paſſe the Night upon my Grave in the Church-yard where I am buried. <hi>Don Diego</hi> ſeeing that the match was like to be very unequal, deſired in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive Language to be excuſed, as not being able to Cope with a Spirit; but the Ghoſt not conſenting, and being ready to fall upon him whether he would or no, <hi>Don Diego</hi> put himſelf into as ſtrong a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture as his fear would let him; immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the dead Man roſe up, and ſhew'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be much above the ſtature of an ordinary Man; at the ſame inſtant, the four Lamps that lighted the room fell down with a horrid noiſe, and the Ghoſt lancing himſelf upon frighted <hi>Don Diego,</hi> ſtruck him down, and left him in a ſwoun, out of which he recovered not till about two hours after; As ſoon as his Spirits were come again, he opened his eyes, and not knowing in what World he was, looked about him, and found that it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35775:34"/>was day: He conſiders the place where he was, ſees nothing but four bare dead Walls; he riſes, and endeavours to find ſome footſteps of thoſe horrid apparitions, but could not ſo much as find the Lamps he had ſeen fall to the ground.</p>
               <p>The day breaking in upon him, gave him courage enough to viſit the reſt of this diſmal houſe, which he did every where, but found nothing but his Sword; he took it and went away, being aſham'd to be ſeen in ſuch a place, though he would fain have informed himſelf of the Neighbours, whoſe houſe it was, and how it came to ſtand thus uninhabited.</p>
               <p>Being come to his own door, he went in, and immediately put himſelf to bed, to refreſh his wearied Limbs, and comfort his affrighted Spirits. The little ſleep he took, was diſturbed with frightfull dreams, and at laſt quite interrupted by a very great knocking at his door; <hi>Almanzor,</hi> who came to him upon the noiſe, talked with him a great while, and heard from him the narration of his whole Adventure, before he would ſtir to let in thoſe, who by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterated knocks did ſeem to be in great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience; at laſt to be delivered of their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35775:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>opportunity, he went to the gate; he that had ſtayed all this while, was one <hi>Don Antonio,</hi> an intimate Friend of <hi>Diegos,</hi> and a very merry Companion: Having ſaluted our Adventurer, he asked him, how he had paſſed his Carnaval? having had ſome ſlight anſwer, For my part, ſaid he, ſtrock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Munchadoes, I failed laſt night of trepanning a fellow, for whom I had prepared a moſt ingenious trap: 'Tis one that you know, 'tis the <hi>Cordouan</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that we call <hi>Don Diego,</hi> but I ſhall have him in one time or another: Why, what is the matter between you? replyed <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugne:</hi> the matter is, anſwered <hi>Don An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio,</hi> that he has vanity enough to be my rival, and to court a rich Lawyers Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whom a Friend of mine long deſigned for his Wife.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt know, that this Ladies Windows look directly upon a certain Church-yard, which gave a pretty hint to my Friend to be revenged of his <hi>Cordouan,</hi> and put an obſtacle to all thoſe walks which he takes on Nights, about her houſe; having heard that <hi>Don Diego</hi> was no very valiant Man, he told him one day in my preſence, that of late there
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35775:35"/>had been buried in that Church-yard, a Man of a notorious ill life, who did alwayes walk there about three of the Clock in the Morning, making fearfull groans, and a dreadfull noiſe of Chains, inſomuch that many of the Inhabitants were ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their Houſes; that therefore he did adviſe him as his Friend, though his Rival, to retire betimes, for fear of ſome ill ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the dead Mans Ghoſt. I joyned my perſwaſions with his, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to increaſe his terrour, by exagerating the honour of the apparition: But here our Gentleman was proof againſt our Plot, for though he made as if he had believed all we ſaid, yet he continued every Night to walk in the ſame place, and give his Miſtreſs Serenados, without fear of being interrupted by the dead Mans groans.</p>
               <p>Our deſign being thus averted, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought my ſelf of another, in which I uſed a much more terrible <hi>apparatus:</hi> I have of late, you muſt know, a houſe thrown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my hands; it ſtands in a by-ſtreet, and a ſolitary part of the Town; and though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers have offered to take it of me, yet I have ſtill deferred letting it, in hopes to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35775:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>make it the Theatre of a piece of revenge, which I had meditated for my Friend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Don Diego</hi> the <hi>Cordouan,</hi> and no later than laſt Night it ſhould have been executed, had not a moſt unlucky accident prevented it.</p>
               <p>I had obliged three Scholars, newly come from the Univerſity, and full of wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh tricks, to undertake the buſineſs; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a falſe pretext, telling them that I had a mind to try the Courage of one of my Friends, who ſeemed to defie all appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Spirits, and Nocturnal Viſions: Thus inſtructed, I led them to my houſe about mid-night, there in a Hall deſigned for the piece, I apparelled two of them like Mourners; the third was a young Stripling almoſt the head and ſhoulders higher than the ordinary ſeize of Men, very ſtrong and active; him I dreſſed in a Winding-ſheet, and made him lie down like a dead Man, at the feet of the others, who were ſitting in two Chairs; the Hall was hung with four Lamps, one at each corner, which yielded a certain gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my light, more horrid than darkneſs it ſelf: Things being thus diſpoſed, I told them that I would preſently ſend them the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35775:36"/>Man I intended to fright, and that as ſoon as he ſhould come in, they ſhould ask him, whether or no his Name were not <hi>Don Diego?</hi> that then they ſhould leave him alone with the dead Man, who was to repreſent ſome body that he had killed, (for I had often heard him brag of the Duels he had fought) and to deſire ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for his death, by wraſtling againſt him: Beſides all this, I left them all free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of invention, and to adde any thing that the occaſion ſhould ſuggeſt, to terrifie our Gentleman the more; this done, I went out, intending to meet <hi>Don Diego,</hi> for I knew where he was, and to lay a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt him, that he durſt not go into my houſe; but unluckily I was diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of my end, for not far from my Houſe, I heard the claſhing of Swords, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, I perceived two of my Friends deſperately engaged with half a dozen <hi>Algouatils,</hi> who would have taken them; I preſently drew in their behalf, and with much ado got them off, but we were ſo warmly purſu'd, that it was all we could do by taking by-lanes and turnings to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape: Before our fray was well ended, and we in a place of ſurety, it was day, and ſo
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35775:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>by conſequent too late to ſeek out <hi>Don Diego;</hi> ſo that I believe my three Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars have ſufficiently curſed me, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them ſit all Night in that mimical dreſſe and poſture.</p>
               <p>While <hi>Antonio</hi> related this ſtory, <hi>Don Diego</hi> did by little and little come to know the cauſe of the misfortune happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by his own curioſity, and the equivocal names of <hi>Don Diego;</hi> having a little admired the ſingularity of the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, he could not chuſe but tell <hi>Don Antonio,</hi> ſmiling, that he had hindred the Scholars from curſing him, and that he could aſſure him <hi>Don Diego</hi> had been there by his means, and that they had perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their parts rarely, and almoſt frighted him out of his Wits: <hi>Antonio</hi> tranſported with joy, asked him, how he came to know any thing of the Plot? whereupon <hi>Don Diego</hi> related to him all his Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, word for word; <hi>Don Antonio,</hi> after he had given great ſigns of his aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, could not chuſe but laugh, though he were ſorry that the effect of a Pagean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try deſign'd for another, had fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own intimate Friend: But <hi>Lucifug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> eaſily forgave him, as being himſelf
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35775:37"/>very glad to ſee that apparition to be but a fiction, which he had taken for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p>After ſome further mirth, <hi>Antonio</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited his Friend to Supper, reſolving like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to ſend for the three Scholars; but when he came home, he was met by two of them, who came to give him an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their ſucceſs; and to tell him withall, that the third verily believing that the Man he had frighted was dead with fear, had taken Sanctuary in an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors houſe, to protect himſelf againſt all purſuits of the Law: Immediately they ſent him word, that he might free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come out, and that if he had a mind to be very merry, he ſhould come and Sup with them, where he ſhould hear a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſtory: he came accordingly, and they were all as jovial, as they had been ſad the Night before. The Supper ended, <hi>Don Diego</hi> went home betimes, to the great content of <hi>Almanzor,</hi> who did begin to hope for a through reformation, ſeeing ſuch good beginnings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35775:37"/>
               <head>Adventure the fifth.</head>
               <p>THe Feaſting and publick Solemnities of the Carnaval being over, <hi>Lent</hi> made its ſolemn entry, with an ugly aſpect to thoſe, who from the exceſſes of the week before, found themſelves reduced to pickl'd Herrings and Ling. <hi>Don Diego,</hi> contrary to <hi>Almanzor's</hi> expectations, was not much troubled at its coming, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were that he was pleaſed with the variety of the Seaſon, or that he did really intend a reform, helived very civilly and modeſtly the firſt weeks of Lent; but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, the greateſt of Virtues and that which Crowns them all, was not at this time given to our Adventurer: For no ſooner did <hi>Eaſter</hi> draw near and the Spring begin to warm the Earth, but <hi>Diego's</hi> blood receiving a new motion from this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of heat, made him ſeek out his old Camerades. He ſoon found them, and began again by little and little to anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate upon the Night, till at laſt he was come to the old paſſe, and did ſeldom retire till <hi>Aurora</hi> with her tears had
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35775:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>treated him like the Flowers, and all bedewed him.</p>
               <p>One day then, or rather one Night, about ten of the Clock, taking his Sword he walked out into the Prado or Hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>park of <hi>Madrid;</hi> every body knows that it is <hi>Venus</hi> Market, and the Fair where the great trade of Love is driven, between the Gallants and Ladies of <hi>Madrid. Don Diego</hi> was juſt come into the Prado, when he eſpyed a Coach, which drave extream ſoftly, and in as great ſtate as if it had been a Queens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the boot was a young Page, who Sung very ill, to a worſe tuned Guittar: The Coach ſtop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in a circle of Gentlemen and Ladies, who were ſitting round a fountain; and immediately the Page, by his Maſters order, began to regale the company with an Atre, but was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with ſo many railleries, that he was glad to hold his Tongue, and his Maſter to make room for a Coach which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: In it was a young Lady of exceeding Beauty, with another old one, and ſhe was ſinging divinely well to a Guittar, which ſhe touched as ſweetly: all the Company drew near at this ſo pleaſant an Harmony, and immediately the Coach was invironed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35775:38"/>by moſt of the Gallants of the Prado; amongſt them there was one, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently leaning upon the boot, took more liberty than any of the reſt, neither did either of the Ladies ſeem to take it ill; there were by a great many others, who would fain have done as much, but wanting confidence durſt not attempt it: While they were all thus attentive to the Ladies Voice, up comes one, almoſt out of breath, having followed the Coach from his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he draws near, and taking notice of the Ladies familiarity with the Gentleman that leaned upon the boot, preſently grew jealous of him, and reſolv'd to quarrel with him; as he was thinking of a pretext, up comes <hi>Don Diego</hi> to him in haſt, being acquainted with him, and deſires him to keep his Guittar for him, while he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two of his Friends, who by their words and actions did ſeem to him to be gone to fight: Our Gentleman, whoſe eyes were fixed upon the Lady in the Coach, took only ſo much notice of <hi>Don Diego's</hi> words and actions, as to take his Guittar, and ſo let him go; he had no ſooner <hi>Don Diego's</hi> inſtrument in his hand, but a ſtring of that on which the Lady played broke;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35775:39"/>immediately he advances very civilly, to preſent the Lady with his, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany might loſe nothing of ſo fine a diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but as he drew near to preſent it, he was puſh'd back with ſcorn by him that leaned upon the boot: immediately <hi>Don Diego's</hi> Friend, reſolving to chaſtiſe his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencies, replies with all his might with the Guittar upon the favourites head, which was bare, and before he could put himſelf in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, had redoubled the blow, &amp; broke the Guittar into a thouſand pieces, as well as the Head in ſome places which run down with blood; immediately they both drew, and all the Company too: The Serjeants, who do ordinarily walk upon the Prado, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome ſuch fray, came in: at their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance <hi>Don Diego's</hi> Friend ſlip'd away in the Croud; the Coach for fear of being ſeized upon, drave away as faſt as four Mules could draw it, and there remained no body there but the wounded Gentleman, and the bruis'd Guittar.</p>
               <p>In this very inſtant back comes <hi>Don Diego,</hi> who had parted his Friends, and was much aſtoniſhed to find ſuch a ſolitude, where a little before he had left ſo great a croud; he walks up and down, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35775:39"/>to find out his Friend the depoſitary of his Guittar: but ſeeing it was in vain, retires very diſconſolate for the loſſe of his dear inſtrument, which had been his faithfull Companion in moſt of his Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; being come home, he ſends to the Gentlemans Lodging; but anſwer was made, that he was gone into the Country, and that they did not know when he would come back.</p>
               <p>The loſſe of the Guittar was the cauſe of <hi>Don Diego's</hi> keeping his Chamber for ſome dayes, where we will leave him, and ſee what became of the wounded favourite. Whether it were the diſgrace of having been beaten before his Miſtreſs, or really the hurts he had received that made him ſo ill, is unknown to this day: but ſo much we have, that he grew worſe and worſe every day, and fell at laſt into a very violent feaver, inſomuch that the Phyſitians and Chirurgions did ſcarce hope for life: in the mean time the criminal Judge did uſe all poſſible means to diſcover the perſon that had brought him into this caſe; and to that end had conſign'd the broken Guittar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one of his Catchpoles hands, who never left poring upon it till he had by putting
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35775:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>all the pieces together, diſcovered at laſt the name of the workman that made it; preſently thinking he had made a happy diſcovery, he goes to him, and asks him if he knew that Guittar; he anſwered, yes, and that he had made it for a Gentleman called <hi>Don Diego;</hi> the Serjeant not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with his naked teſtimony, asks his journeymen; who confirming their Maſters words, he ſummons them all immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to come and depoſe the ſame upon Oath before the Judge: They not daring to refuſe, go and juſtifie what they had ſaid to be true; the Judge forbids them as they would anſwer it at their perill, to give any notice of their depoſition to <hi>Don Diego:</hi> But no ſooner were they out of his ſight, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the injury they had unwarily done to a Gentleman their cuſtomer, they went unanimouſly and gave him informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the danger he was in. <hi>Don Diego,</hi> who was very innocent, fell into a great rage againſt the malicious Catchpole; he by the advice of <hi>Almanzor,</hi> immediately ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured all his goods in an Ambaſſadours Houſe hard by his, having got acquainted before with his Secretary; then he retired thither himſelf, and kept cloſe for a matter
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35775:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>of three weeks or thereabouts; during that time, the great care that was taken of the ſick man, who was a perſon of condition, had good ſucceſs, and he recovered ſo well as to be out of danger; upon that, ſome propoſitions of agreement, and tender of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction were made, which by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lady, for whom the quarrel had hapned, were after ſome diſpute accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Gentleman <hi>Don Diego's</hi> Friend came back and ſhewed himſelf again; he preſented <hi>Don Diego</hi> with a very fine new Guittar, and all was well.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Don Diego,</hi> who was of a very vindicative nature, being not at all ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that the malicious Catchpole, who had laid him up ſo long, ſhould go away Scot-free, at laſt never left contriving till he had bethought himſelf of ſome piece of revenge, where neither he nor his Friends might run any hazard; and at laſt after much ſtudy and labour he was delivered of the following deſign.</p>
               <p>During his ſtay at the Ambaſſadours Houſe, he had got acquaintance with ſome witty young Men, who had taken ſhelter there as well as himſelf: One day then he invited them to Supper, where be
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35775:41"/>ſpared no coſt to put them in good hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. The firſt health they drank was the Ambaſſadours, who afforded them the protection of his Houſe; the ſecond was the magnificent <hi>Don Diego's,</hi> at whoſe coſt and charges they were then ſo merry; the third was the Lawyers and Attornies, who did protect them with their eloquence and ſhifts, againſt the ſeverity of the Law; the fourth was to the Brokers, who did buy of them, and ſo induſtriouſly alter the Cloaks they did uſe to nim in the Night; the fifth was to the Vintners, who did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten give them credit, and by that means afforded them the occaſion of bubling a young Whelp; thus they went on till they were all pretty well gone.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Don Diego</hi> having propoſed to them his intention, they all conſented to it, and four of the moſt determined amongſt them undertook it: They cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves in black Serge from top to toe, putting upon their heads great horns, and behind them great tails of two yards long, which <hi>Don Diego</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; in this equipage, as like Devils as they could make themſelves, they march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, and getting over the wall of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35775:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>yard where the Sergeants houſe ſtood, they broke into it, and with a horrid noiſe running up Stairs, dragged him out of his bed from his Wife; there they whipped him ſo long, till they had uſed all the bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels of rods they had brought with them, and drawn ſo much blood of him, as caſt the poor man into a Swoun; but they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to leave him in his ſenſes, that he might remember his puniſhment, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued on clawing of him, till out of the extremity of pain they brought him to himſelf again; the firſt word he ſaid when he opened his eyes, was, <hi>Jeſus;</hi> at the ſound of that Name, they all forſook him, and vaniſhing immediately, confirmed him and his Wife in the opinion, that they were true Devils: The Sergeant lay upon the floor of his Houſe a long time, while his diſmayed Wife was hid in the ſheets, and all in a could ſweat, ſo that it was day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he got to bed again, and then he was ſo ſore with the ſtripes he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that he was hardly well in a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night.</p>
               <p>The noiſe of this ſo ſtrange an accident, was in the mean time ſpread all the Town over, and every body had a curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35775:42"/>to ſee the Catchpole, that had been chaſtiſed by the Devils themſelves, ſo that he durſt not ſtir out when he was well, for fear of being pointed at in the Streets. <hi>Don Diego</hi> hearing all this, thought himſelf well revenged, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately retired to his own Houſe, where for two dayes he lived modeſtly, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his Night-walks again.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:35775:42"/>
               <head>Adventure the ſixth.</head>
               <p>THe harbingers of ſleep, wearineſs and yawning, did begin to ſummon the Sun to retire to his bed in the Sea, which is juſtly reſerved for him alone, (for being of ſo fiery and dry a complexion, few be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelf can like a Couch ſo wet and ſo cold) when our generous <hi>Don Diego,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill Diſciple of his own experiences, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſeek out new dangers, or rather to meet them half way, for they ſeldom avoided him: The Night was quite blind, and had not ſo much as the glimmering of a few Stars to light its Friends, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more welcome to <hi>Don Diego;</hi> but before we enter any further into the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, we muſt make a little degreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>There was at <hi>Sevill</hi> a Man of a lofty mean, who wore good Cloaths and paſſed for a Gentleman, but was indeed a Shark; his Name was <hi>Don Diego,</hi> and moſt of his tricks be plaied in the Night; he was ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the <hi>Nocturne,</hi> ſo that there appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the World two <hi>Don Diegos</hi> of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35775:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſame Name, ours being called ſometimes <hi>Lueifugne,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Nocturne:</hi> Our <hi>Sevilian</hi> ſeeing that his life was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at <hi>Sevill,</hi> and that the many robberies he had committed, would in the end lodge him in a place of perpetual darkneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd rather to be eclipſed for a while, and to ſteal away; he gave out cunningly, that he was going for <hi>Madrid,</hi> but the day that he abſented himſelf from <hi>Sevill,</hi> he took <hi>Grenada</hi> road, hoping to be very welcome in that place, which affords ordinarily a favourable acceſs to Strangers.</p>
               <p>The report of his journey to <hi>Madrid</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publiſhed, and come to the ears of a Merchant, whom he had cheated of ſome Rings, the Merchant without more ado gets up, and to the no ſmall loſs of his skin, which the Mules hard trot and ſaddle did ſufficiently wear away, came to <hi>Madrid;</hi> there having ſent a note to all the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths, to apprehend the Man if he ſhould come to ſell the ſaid Jewels, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured beſides to ſtrike into moſt wilde Companies, hoping to diſcover his Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in ſome ſuch gang.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Night after the coming of the Jeweler, our primitive <hi>Don Diego</hi> ſet
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35775:43"/>out again upon the queſt of ſome new <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture:</hi> He had got acquaintance with a young Solicitours Wife, a very pretty Woman, who had the reputation of a great deal of Wit, and much of ſubtilty; the glory of over-reaching all her cunning, and gaining with eaſe one who was ſo well fortified againſt the attaques of all others, had engaged <hi>Don Diego</hi> in this Siege, and in it he had been ſo fortunate, that with the loſs of very little time, but by the help of an induſtrious old Woman, he had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly undermined the place, and brought it to capitulate; the articles were, that it ſhould be delivered up to him that Night between twelve and one of the Clock, but that he ſhould not fail to bring along with him two rings of good value, which the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy had ſeen upon his fingers, to be as it were hoſtages of good behaviour on his part. <hi>Diego</hi> promiſed he would, and though he had ſet a greater value upon the Rings, becauſe they had been his Mothers, yet being accuſtomed to ſacrifice all things to his ſenſuality, he yielded to that article; the next was, that he ſhould lay by all the ſigns of a Gentleman, <hi>viz.</hi> his Cloaths and his Guittar, and come diſguiſed like a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35775:44"/>man, to the end that if he were by chance met either coming in or going out, the Lady might ſay that he was a fellow come from her Mothers in the Country, and to that end, ſhe put into his hands one of her Mothers Letters, which ſhe had new ſealed up; laſtly, that he ſhould climb over an old Wall, and ſo by the Garden, of the door of which ſhe gave him a key, come into a little ſummer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, where he ſhould find the Lady diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to receive and content him: <hi>Don Diego</hi> having ſigned all theſe articles, ſet out from his own Houſe about the hour of aſſignation; as he came into the Street where his Miſtreſs houſe ſtood, he heard in paſſing by a door a very great noiſe, as of people in a tumult; thereupon he ſteps in, the door being open, and ſees a Man wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the bottom of a Barrel, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who lighted him with a Candle in a Lanthorn, for fear the Wind ſhould blow it out: Round about them ſtood a great many others, ſome without Stockings, others without Doublets, and others in their Shirts with their Cloaks over, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving almoſt all Swords under their Arms. Oar Adventurer ſtood a pretty while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35775:44"/>them, to hearken to what they were ſaying, without being perceived, and found that ſome body had been rob'd in the Neighbourhood, and knew the Man who was writing for the Clark of criminal Cauſes, who was taking the depoſition of the Witneſſes; having thus contented his curioſity, he thought fit to retire; but as ill luck would have it, he was ſurpriſed with a fit of ſneezing, which he could not Maſter; the noiſe made the others face about, and ask, Who's there? <hi>Don Diego</hi> not willing to be taken notice of in his diſguiſe, began to haſten away, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to avoid their purſuit at the next turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But his haſte increaſing the others ſuſpicion, they ran after him with a full cry, <hi>ſtop thief, ſtop thief;</hi> Our Friend, who could not endure any offence in his humour, turns back upon thoſe words, and with <hi>(you lye, you dogs)</hi> cuts the foremoſt over the pate, and laies him at his feet; the others exaſperated by the blow, fell upon him, and in ſpight of his reſiſtance did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm him, and carry him before the Clark of the criminal Cauſes.</p>
               <p>There was nothing in his perſon, that might not in ſome ſort ſerve to convict
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35775:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>him, for his mean and his Cloaths were not all ſuitable; beſides, having ſearched him, they found in his pocket a little box, wherein were the two Rings, the Letter, and a Key, which was that of his Miſtreſſes Garden door; the Clark divided the ſpoil very equally, taking for himſelf the two Rings, and giving the Catchpole his aſſiſtant the Letter and the Key; that done, he ſent <hi>Don Diego</hi> to Priſon, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his proteſtations, that he was a Gentleman, and a Perſon of Quality; who would make them repent their inſolency; they dragg'd him along, and the Jaylor for his welcome put him into the Dungeon to two true thieves, that had been taken in the very act of that robbery: They hearing him talk much of his quality and Friends, reſolv'd as ſoon as they ſhould be confronted to him, to ſay that he was one of their complices, to the end that by his Friends means they might be all ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd: Whereupon the next, they charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him home with all the robbery, and put him into a moſt violent rage againſt their knavery, but all to no other purpoſe, than to make the noiſe of him ſeem more guilty.</p>
               <p>In the morning as ſoon as this capture
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35775:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>and impriſonment of Thieves was abroad, divers of <hi>Don Diego's</hi> Friends came to be bail for his appearance, but he had not ſo much liberty granted him as to ſpeak with them, ſo that they were fain to return, and expect the event of the buſineſs by the Law.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the report growing publick, came to the ear of our <hi>Sevilian</hi> Jeweler; who hearing of Jewels ſeiſed in the Pocket of one <hi>Don Diego,</hi> made no doubt but it was the Man he hunted after, and came in great haſte firſt to the Clarks to ſeiſe and claim the Rings, then to the Priſon, to charge the Priſoner with new crimes; he imployed in the purſuit of his buſineſs the Solicitour, husband to the fair Lady who was to have granted <hi>Don Diego</hi> a better Nights lodging, than that which his hard Fortune had provided for him; he coming to inform himſelf more particularly of the buſineſs, found the Letter directed to his Wife, and the Key of one of his Doors; upon that he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that there had been a deſign to rob his houſe too, and immediately put in a new charge upon the Priſoner, deſiring he might be interrogated upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:35775:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>The proceſs being in this condition, <hi>Don Diego</hi> could do no leſſe than give private notice to the Lady, to deſire her to cauſe her husband to deſiſt from his violent purſuit, or elſe that he ſhould be forced in his own defence to diſcover all the intrigue; but ſhe being a perfect coquet, was already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in other Amours, and little minded <hi>Diego's</hi> advertiſement; this being related to <hi>Don Diego</hi> again by his old Ambaſſadreſs, he reſolv'd to clear himſelf of the infamy and oppreſſion he lay under; and therefore ſent for one of his intimate Friends, who was likewiſe familiar with the Judge, and laid open to him all the myſtery: he told the Judge of it, who told him, that <hi>Don Diego</hi> muſt prove what he ſaid; thereupon the old Woman was heard, who diſcovered the aſſignation: The Letter was produced, and the <hi>Sevilian</hi> Jeweler being brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Don Diego,</hi> confeſſed to his great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement, that he was not the Man that he looked for; thereupon the Judge ſet him at liberty; ordered the Rings to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to him; to the Solicitour the Keys of his Door, and to his Wife the Letter. After the pronouncing of this juſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, the Merchant and the Solicitour
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35775:46"/>ſtood amaz'd, and looking upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and at laſt went away, both with three inches of noſe, and the Solicitour with a famous pair of horns, which with much eare and induſtry he had planted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own head: <hi>Don Diego</hi> retired, ſmiling to ſee their dejected countenance, and was very glad that the accident had hindred him from going to the aſſignation, where infallibly he had parted with his Rings; Thus ending this Adventure, we may conclude with the proverb, <hi>That ill luck is good for ſomething.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <head>Adventure the ſeventh.</head>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:35775:47"/>
               <p>THough our incomparable <hi>Don Diego</hi> were come off with flying Colours from this laſt engagement with his ill fortune, being abſolv'd from all the crimes which had been laid to his charge; yet he reſolved to inflict a voluntary puniſhment upon himſelf, and for a while to leave <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid.</hi> 'Tis true, that his baniſhment could not be very rigorous, fince one of the main motives of his journey, was to receive two thouſand Ducats, which were due to him at <hi>Salamanca:</hi> In this City is the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Spain,</hi> and ordinarily a very great concourſe of Scholars, to partake in the fertility of all the Sciences, which ſeem there to have choſen their ſeat. <hi>Don Diego</hi> had to do with ſuch good pay-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that no ſooner did they hear of his arrival, but they brought him his money to his Lodging: Nevertheleſſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd not to go back ſo ſoon, but ſpent ſome time in the converſation of the moſt learned and ingenious of the Profeſſors and Scholars, to his very great advantage:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35775:47"/>At laſt, doubly enriched, he returned to <hi>Madrid,</hi> and locked up his Ducats very carefully, as reſolving to inſpire them with ſomething of his humour, and to let them ſee day as ſeldom as he could; the two firſt Nights were devoted to the reſt of his wearied Perſon, but the third he reſolv'd to walk out, for fear of being guilty of violating his own freedom and natural Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges; but he was prevented from exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting his deſign, by divers viſits of his Friends, and amongſt others there came a certain Perſon whom the World call'd the <hi>Knight of Wonders,</hi> becauſe that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any viſible revenue or income, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd very handſomly at Court, wearing as good Cloathes as any body, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as handſome a Retinue; this did make many ſuſpect, that he had ſome flight of hand, to convey other peoples money inviſibly to his own purſe: <hi>Don Diego</hi> gave him an ample recital of his journey, and the happy ſucceſs of it; ſhewing him withall his Ducats, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm what he ſaid; the Knight congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulated his happy return, and having given him an account of the Town, and all the News, took his leave, though
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35775:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> would have made him ſtay Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
               <p>It was paſt mid-night before our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer could get clear of two or three viſits more, but at laſt the viſitants being all gone, he took his Sword and walked out; his firſt reflections were upon the imprudent action he had done, in ſhewing his Ducats to the Knight of Wonders, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much troubled leſt he ſhould conſpire againſt the quiet which he had propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to himſelf in the enjoyment of them: In this thought he reſolves to go back, and to hide them in another place, that at leaſt he might diſappoint the aim of ſuch as ſhould endeavour to get them from him. As he was going back, he took his way through a Church-yard, which was hard by his Houſe, and heard a Voice, which was mingled with ſighs and groans, and which did ſeem to come from a Houſe where they had laid up the dead Mens bones; he ſtops at that, and hears it again; imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately conſidering that it was an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſhewing his Courage, and ſuch a one as would make him paſs for a Heroes if he came off well, he reſolv'd to go on towards the Voice: Drawing near, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35775:48"/>a very weak light, which did break through a ſeparation of Boards, which divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Houſe from the reſt of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; that guided him to the door, which a little about, and juſt as he was going in, was he trod upon a dead Mans rib, which brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king under him, had like to have given him a fall; at the noiſe, a mans voice cried, Who goes there? and immediately <hi>Don Diego</hi> ſaw a Perſon of a noble mean come towards him, having his Sword drawn in one hand, and a dark Lanthorn in the other; at the ſight of the naked Sword, <hi>Don Diego</hi> immediately drew, and was putting himſelf in a poſture of defence, when he heard himſelf named, and knew the Voice to be that of the Knight of Wonders: <hi>Diego</hi> full of admiration, asks him, What he did there? Alas! my dear Friend, anſwered the Knight, you find me here in the greateſt perplexity imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; a young Lady of quality, whom I have privately married, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of her Friends, is here juſt now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered; for you muſt know, that having lived in her Fathers Houſe all the time ſince our marriage, ſhe let me know this morning, that, ſhe did begin to feel
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35775:49"/>ſome ſymptoms of her labour, and beg'd of me that I would convey her away from her Friends, fearing a hard uſage from her Father, who is a moſt paſſionate Man: I not knowing in ſo ſhort a time whither to carry her; was reſolved to have brought her to your houſe, as knowing your frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and generoſity to diſtreſſed Perſons; but by the way ſhe was ſo overcome with her pains, that we were glad to get into this Charner-houſe, where ſhe is juſt now delivered: At that they drew near, and <hi>Diego</hi> ſaw with amazement a young per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of admirable beauty, lying in a weak condition upon a heap of dead Mens bones, and a Childe newly born by her, which by its cries ſeem'd to bemoan its deſtiny in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born in the very Empire of Death: In this confuſion, the Father takes the Childe, and wrapping it in his Cloak went away, recommending the mother to <hi>Don Diego</hi> s care, who remained there all alone with a Lanthorn in his hand, comforting the poor diſconſolate Lady. But for an increaſe of misfortune, the wax-candle which was in the Lanthorn was at an end, ſo that going out, it left him &amp; the Lady all alone in the dark, the terrour of which was
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35775:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>much augmented by the native horrour of the place.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, while our Charitable Adventurer was thus employed, one of the ſubtleſt thieves in all <hi>Madrid</hi> had ſet ſpies upon his Ducats, and having advice that he had forſook the guard of them that night, made haſte to uſe the happy occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; he picked all the locks of the Houſe, and took the money, divers jewels, and two very good ſutes of Cloathes: he makes a bundle of all this, and wing'd with ſpeed and fear, gets away ſafe into the Street. He had not gone above a Streets length, when he heard the Watch coming that way; whereupon being well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all by-paſſages, he ſlips cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Church-yard hard by, and coming into the Charner-houſe where <hi>Don Diego</hi> and his Lady were, throws down by them his bundle: The Lady was frighted, and <hi>Don Diego</hi> immediately with his Sword drawn, goes towards him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very ignorant of the Preſent which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune did make him of his own goods: The thief hearing ſome body walk upon the dead mens bones, and frighted beſides with his own guilty Conſcience, runs away as
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35775:50"/>hard as he can drive; juſt coming out of the Church-yard, he meets the Watch, who went about to lay hold on him, as a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Perſon; but the imagination of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purſued by a Ghoſt, gave him courage enough to force his way through them with a quarter-ſtaff, which he underſtood the uſe of very well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> hearing no more noiſe, thought it not diſcretion to follow any further, and leave the diſtreſſed Lady alone; he therefore went back to her, and found that ſhe had recovered a little ſtrength; whereupon he propoſed to her, to lead her to one of his ſervants Houſes, who was married and lived there hard by; ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, &amp; they were very courteouſly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when the people of the houſe ſaw their maſter <hi>Don Diego;</hi> as ſoon as lights were brought, and that <hi>Don Diego</hi> could freely contemplate the face of the Perſon he had done ſo good an office to, it was all he could do to refrain from falling at her knees, ſo admirable was her beauty; and certainly, had not the concern for his Ducats, and his uſual trueneſs to his Friend, been his Antidotes, he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have kept the Poyſon of Love from
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35775:50"/>killing all his reaſon. Immediately a Mid-wife was ſent for to tend the Lady, who was put into an excellent bed: There let us leave her, and ſee what became in the mean time of her lover the Knight of Wonders.</p>
               <p>He having found a Nurſe with much trouble, and being yet deſirous to ſtay a little to ſee the Childe tended, it being ſomewhat ill, deſired the Nurſes Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to go and excuſe his delay to <hi>Don Diego</hi> and his Lady, and intreat him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of her ſomewhere, where ſhe might receive help and aſſiſtance; when this Man came to the Church-yard, <hi>Don Diego</hi> was already gone; the man coming in, finds no body there, whereupon he makes haſte to get out of ſo horrid a place, and as he was near the door, ſets his foot upon the bundle which the thief had thrown there; finding it yield under him, he thought it was ſome dead mans body, and giving a great ſhreek, was ready to run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, when by the favour of his Lanthorn he perceived his errour; he views the bundle, and ſeeing the outſide pretty rich, begins to deliberate, whether or no he ſhould carry it away: He eaſily concluded to the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35775:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>affirmative, thinking it no ſmall favour of his fortune to meet with ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel in a place where every body comes naked.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> all this while, having ſeen the Lady well diſpoſed of, thought that how he might pay a viſit to his Ducats, which had run in his mind ever ſince his going out; he comes to his Houſe, goes ſtreight up to the Chamber where his Cabinet ſtood, and finds the doors of it open, and his Money gone, as well as his Jewels and Cloathes; immediately not knowing whom to accuſe, he ſuſpects the Knight of Wonders to be the author of this feat, and that he had taken the time to do it, while he was buſie in conducting the ſick Lady to a place of ſafety and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment. This thought having tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported him with anger, he immediately went out, reſolving to go ſtraight to the Church-yard, whither it was probable that the Knight would come, that he might ſeem leſſe guilty.</p>
               <p>As good luck was, <hi>Don Diego</hi> came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church-yard, juſt as the man whom the Knight of Wonders had ſent to him, was getting up his bundle, and going away
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35775:51"/>with it; ſuddenly <hi>Don Diego</hi> blinded with rage, falls upon him, taking him for the Knight, and not only made him looſe his hold, but threatned to have him hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: At that very inſtant a Catchpole who had in vain wandered all Night in hopes of a prey, comes in at the noiſe, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Men ſtrugling about a bundle, commands them in the Kings Name to keep the Peace, and anſwer his interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; and in <hi>Spain</hi> every petty offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of Juſtice being much reſpected, he was preſently obeyed. The day was juſt then breaking, and <hi>Don Diego's</hi> anger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little evaporated in the ſcuffle, gave him leave to conſider the man he had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taqu'd, and to perceive his miſtake; on the other ſide, the man ſeeing that no body did lay hold on him, and being afraid leſt being found ſeiſed of an unknown bundle, he might be called in queſtion for ſtealing of it, ſlunk away very diligently, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Don Diego</hi> to anſwer the Catch pole: Juſt as he was beginning his examination, in comes the true thief, who had ſtayed till it was day, to come and fetch from the dead the Packet of which he had made them receivers; he perceives <hi>Don Diego</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:35775:52"/>and the Serjeant diſputing together, he draws near, and being a very bold fellow, and of a preſent Wit, comes to them with his hat in his hand, as if he had been ſome ordinary perſon drawn thither by his curioſity; the Serjeant after ſome diſpute, having touched <hi>Don Diego</hi> with his wand, and commanded him to follow, bids this thief, the ſtander by, to take up the bundle, and come along with them to the Judge: As they went, the cunning rogue takes the firſt turning, and ſlips away; a little after, <hi>Diego</hi> looking about, miſſes him, and tells the Catchpole angerly, that he ſhould be reſponſible to him for that bundle; the Catchpole taking him to have been of the confederacy with the other, and vexed to ſee ſuch a trick put upon himſelf, anſwers very ſawcily, in ſo much that our Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer not able to endure it, draws and cuts him over the pate; at the Catchpoles out-cry, the Neighbours came out, and <hi>Don Diego</hi> is ſeiſed and carried before a Magiſtrate, who having learned his quality, and the nature of the buſineſs, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to give him his own houſe for Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and two Serjeants to guard him.</p>
               <p>The Knight of Wonders in the interim,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35775:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>impatient to hear from his dear Lady, goes to the Church-yard, and from thence, finding no body there, runs to <hi>Don Diego's</hi> houſe, at which place he heard of his being robb'd, but could get no account of his diſtreſſed Wife; not knowing whither to go next, he reſolv'd to ſee whither his Nurſes Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was come back again or no; but he was in a ſtrange perplexity, when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the houſe he found the Woman in ſuch a fright, that all her milk was gone, and ſo the poor infant in danger of being famiſhed: the buſineſs was, that her Husband had come to her almoſt out of breath, and told her, that he muſt run away for fear of being apprehended for a certain bundle of Cloathes, of which he had been found ſeiſed, and which were ſtollen goods: At this new accident the Knight of Wonders was extreamly troubled, and all that he could do in order to the preſervation of the Childs life, was preſently to hire a Coach, and taking the infant with him, carry it to a little vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage within a League of <hi>Madrid,</hi> where people uſed to put their Children out to Nurſe. The true thief did no ſooner ſee himſelf at liberty, but without any more
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35775:53"/>delay, for fear of ſome new accident, he reſolv'd to leave <hi>Madrid,</hi> which he did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, hoping to enjoy his prey in quiet. The ſick Lady was infinitely tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented to ſee her ſelf forſaken by her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Don Diego</hi> was almoſt mad to find himſelf a priſoner, and ſo hindred from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Knight of Wonders; and in a word, there was a general confuſion amongſt all theſe Perſons; but Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at laſt unridled all theſe myſteries, and gave a quiet calm, inſtead of theſe ſtorms.</p>
               <p>The Knight of Wonders being come to <hi>Checafé,</hi> for ſo was the Village called, made ſuch diligence that in leſſe than an hour he found a Nurſe, and was with the like haſte getting up into his Coach to return to <hi>Madrid,</hi> when he heard a very great noiſe in the Inn where he was, and going in, found a Man who had ſeiſed another, and was ready to ſtrangle him; crying, traytor, rogue, I am the Man thou didſt rob about a year ago at <hi>Toledo,</hi> and I will now have thy life for my ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; at this mans out-cries the people came in, and the Knight of Wonders draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near, and putting ſome queſtions to the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35775:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>other about the bundle he ſaw there with him, began to ſuſpect that he might be <hi>Don Diego's</hi> thief; immediately the Judge of the place was ſent for, in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence the bundle was open'd, and an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventory made of all that was found, to which the Knight of Wonders laied claim for his Friend. The thief was clap'd up, and the Knight went back poſt to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> to carry <hi>Don Diego</hi> theſe glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; who to requite his favour, carried him to ſee his diſtreſſed Wife, who was drowned in tears for his abſence; there by the Ladys own confeſſion <hi>Don Diego</hi> learned, that it was by her means, who was the only Daughter of a rich Man, that the Knight of Wonders did ſubſiſt ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely; whereupon he was very ſorry that he had harboured ſo ill an opinion of his Friend, but yet very glad there was no ground for it. Leaving the two Lovers to their mutual enjoyment, he went to the Judge, who had given him his houſe for Priſon, and having acquainted him with the buſineſs, eaſily obtained a Commiſſary to go and fetch the thief, and his thieft. The one was hanged, and the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to <hi>Don Diego,</hi> not without ſome
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35775:54"/>diminution, as having paſt through the hands of the Officers of Juſtice: Being once again in poſſeſſion of his Ducats, he reſolved to keep them with more care hereafter, and in the mean time for an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of their recovery, he thought himſelf bound to aſſiſt the Knight of Wonders his Friend, in appeaſing and ſoftning the angry Parents of his Wife; who when they ſhould come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their Daughters action, whom they now lamented as loſt, would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſinherit her: he by the aſſiſtance of a great many people of quality, his intimate Friends, laboured ſo effectually in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that at laſt the Father and Mother ſeeing there was no remedy, and being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that the Knight of Wonders was of an ancient Family, though poor, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the match; the more to ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize this happy ſucceſs, there was a great meeting of kindred and Friends, where the VVedding was kept in great ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> much pleaſed at his Friends good Fortune, made a new League of Friendſhip with him, and one would have thought, that having ſo many times tried the fickleneſs of fortune, he ſhould at laſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35775:54"/>have been content to take her and marry her, while ſhe was in a good fit, rather than be expoſed to court once more in his adverſity; but ſucceſs makes men impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and ſo it did our Adventurer, who expos'd himſelf to new dangers, as we ſhall ſee in the following Adventure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <head>Adventure the eighth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DOn Diego</hi> having experienced a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient variety of accidents in the Streets of <hi>Madrid,</hi> did begin to be afraid leſt at laſt he ſhould be forced to give over his extravagant Life, for want of novelty in his Adventures; while he was in this concern, he learned that the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots which paſſe that Sea of durt in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and clouds of duſt in Summer, which is between <hi>Madrid</hi> and <hi>Toledo,</hi> did go in the night time for coolneſs ſake: Upon that conſideration, he thought that a little Country air would do him no hurt, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſince he could take it without
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35775:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeeing the Sun, with whoſe beams he was at feud; he takes up a place, and was not a little pleaſed in his imagination, to think what a pleaſure it would be to him to hear diſcourſe of the meaner ſort of people, who ordinarily take that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience. The Company was compoſed of four Clowns, a poor Fryer, and <hi>Don Diego;</hi> as ſoon as they were out of Town, every one began to relate his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures; the one b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aging how he had made his Camerade drunk, and left him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; the other how he had pick'd his Fathers Pocket the Night before, to get as much money as would defray him to <hi>Toledo,</hi> and make him merry by the way; and a third relating how he had not taken his leave of any body, leſt ſome who were his Creditors ſhould have deſired him to ſtay a little longer than would have been convenient for him, and that in an ugly houſe, called a Priſon: All theſe confeſſions came freely out, and almoſt all ſpeaking together, ſo that the noiſe was ſo great, that had <hi>Don Diego</hi> had a mind to put in, there had been no room for a word of his; with this odd entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they came to <hi>Illeſcas;</hi> as ſoon as
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35775:55"/>they ſtop'd at the Inn, and were ready to light, one of the Company miſs'd his bag, and preſently charged the Coach-man with it; he denying that he ever ſaw it, from words they fell to blows, and the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff Clown being aſſiſted by the reſt of his gang, proved too hard for the Coach-man Defendant, inſomuch that they left him upon the ſtones for dead; at the noiſe the Inn-keeper, ſolicited by his daughter, who had commiſerated the fall of her poor <hi>Phaeton,</hi> came out with his ſervants, and then the fray begun anew, though the Fryer on one hand, and <hi>Don Diego</hi> on the other, did uſe very peaceable interpoſitions and exhortations. The rumour continuing, brought the Judge and his Officers upon them, who began with ſeiſing the Chariot and its Mules, then fell on the parties, and had in his general capture comprehended our Friend <hi>Don Diego,</hi> for all his modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if ſome Country Gentlemen coming in had not known him, and anſwered for his appearance, if need were; and indeed he had ſo diſguiſed himſelf in conformity to his Company, that it was no wonder he was like to ſuffer with them; whereby a Man may learn, that it is no ill maxim
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35775:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>to wear good Cloathes, when you are in a place where few people know who you are, for then they ſpeak for you, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to people of quality. Our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer having met in the Inn a very pretty Lady of pleaſure, ſtaied at <hi>Illeſcas</hi> for her ſake five or ſix daies, ſhe having given him certain liberties, which had made him looſe his own to her for a while; the cure of this his Amorous diſeaſe, was not performed without ſome bleeding from his Purſe, which is a ſort of evacuation which to many people is more painfull than that of their Veins: As ſoon as he was well, he took leave of his Doctor, who would willingly have continued on to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and hired a Mule; paſſing thus from one Mounture to another, and finding little difference in the hardſhip of their trots, but much in their vigour, for this laſt was almoſt ſtarved, and ſo weary that it did threaten him with a fall at every ſtep; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for about a League gone very ſoftly, and yet perpetually tottering, he reſolv'd to try what effect his ſpurs would produce, and clapping them to the Beaſts ſide, made it in an endeavour to advance tumble head over heels with our <hi>Don Diego,</hi> who had
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35775:56"/>enough to do to free himſelf from his ſtirrops, being ſufficiently mauled with his fall; he got up, and chooſing rather to go a foot, than try his fate again upon ſuch a ruinous Creature, was well content to lead it by the bridle, and ſo crawl to the next Inn, where he arrived about break of day, having according to his cuſtom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun his journey in the night; he got a very good Breakfaſt, or rather a good Supper, for with him the evening was Dinner, and the morning Supper time; and then he went to bed, ſleeping like one that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cares of mind, nor indiſpoſition of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy did afflict.</p>
               <p>About four of the Clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon he was waked with the ſound of a Poſt-boys horn, and looking out of his window, perceived that it was an <hi>Alguaſil</hi> riding poſt; he came into the Inn and let the Maſter know, that he had a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the high Counſell to ſearch all publick houſes along the road for certain thieves, who had committed a very great robbery at <hi>Madrid;</hi> the choiſe that had been made of his perſon for ſuch an inquiry, being grounded on the ſingular skill he had in making ſuch diſcoveries, in which
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35775:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>he often went ſnips with the thieves them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as being the greateſt of them all: The Maſter at the ſight of his order, cauſed all his gueſts to come forth and appear, and <hi>Don Diego</hi> had been certainly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for the ſake of his ill Cloaths, had not the <hi>Alguaſil</hi> by chance knew him.</p>
               <p>The Officer having made a very diligent perquiſition to no purpoſe, was about to continue on his way, when <hi>Don Diego</hi> and he walking out at the gate, perceived a good way off, at the entry of the Village, a Funeral coming; it was a Bier carried by two luſtyMules, and attended with four Mourners, and four Monks, all in black: the Monks ſtop'd at the coming in to the Village, and calling the people about them, deſired them to joyn in prayer for the dead Man whom they conveyed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon began to ſing the office for the dead; the <hi>Alguaſil</hi> and <hi>Don Diego,</hi> not to ſeem irreligious, drew near, and after their ſhort Commemoration was ended, having caſt ſome holy Water upon the Body, asked one of the Monks, if they had not met people in ſuch and ſuch habits; he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering no, the other asked them, if they
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35775:57"/>had not heard of a great robbery commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Madrid;</hi> yes, ſayes the Fryer, and here with us is the thieft which a great thief has boldly achieved; where is it, ſaid the <hi>Alguaſil,</hi> very much concerned; Alas, Sir, ſaid the Monk, the thieft is in the Bier, and the thief is death; come Sir, ſaid he, taking the <hi>Alguaſil</hi> by the hand, and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him towards the Bier, come and ſee to what poor mortals are ſubject; the <hi>Alguaſil</hi> who hated any thing that did put him in mind of dying, drew back, and getting looſe from the Monk, pray Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaid he, let me alone, I am not here to controle the actions of death, neither do I delight in ſeeing ſuch ſpectacles; after this he made haſte to get up and away.</p>
               <p>The Officer being gone, <hi>Don Diego</hi> took up with the conveyers of the dead body; they unloaded their Mules un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a great porch, and cauſed a table to be covered hard by the Bier, from which they ſtirred not all the time; they had beſpoke an excellent Supper, and ſeeing <hi>Don Diego</hi> all alone, invited him to take part of it; he who was not at all ceremonious, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides very inquiſitive naturally into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35775:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>of all ſorts of people, accepted their kind offer; they were very merry, and not at all ſparing of the delicious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, drinking their healths and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round; the Miſtreſs of the houſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mourners and the Monks, who pretended to ſo much mortification, uſe ſo little, even when they had an example of death before their eyes, told them mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, that they did well to make good chear and rejoyce, for, ſaid ſhe, I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain there are enough that lament and take on for that poor perſon which you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey: Truly Madam, anſwer'd the chief, who ſat at the upper end of the table, you have ſaid a thing which is moſt certain; for without doubt there is at this preſent a very great affliction in the Houſe out of which this rich body came, and not a poor body as you call it; and that which moſt grieves the family, is the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſudden death; alas! he dyed in my arms, and I my ſelf wraped him up in his winding ſheet: Be not therefore ſcandalized to ſee us take our refection with ſome jollity, for beſides our ſhare of grief for his loſs, that of labour and toil in going thus a foot to convoy him to his
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35775:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sepulchre, is very great: Saying this, he filled a glaſs of Wine, and drank to <hi>Don Diego</hi> the Miſtreſs health; at laſt by this carouſing, one of the Company having a weaker brain than the reſt, grew very ſick, and having vomited under the table, fell a ſleep in the ſame place, keeping time with his ſnooring, to the noiſe the others made with their talking.</p>
               <p>About ten a clock at Night, they that had moſt of their Wits about them, thought it was time to be marching, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far from their deſign to lie in the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage all Night; whereupon they loaded their Mules, and payed their hoſteſs very well, recommending to her care their drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Companion; and having firſt taken from him his mourning gown, they were ſolicitous with her to get them another man in his room, to help to guide their Mules, promiſing to content him very well. <hi>Don Diego</hi> immediately, tempted by his own deviliſh curioſity, and deſirous to know to what place it was that they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the body, offered to ſupply the room of him whom wine and ſleep had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled: They received him very gladly, and immediately ſet out, ſinging a <hi>requiem
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35775:59"/>aeternam</hi> to the health of the dead mans ſoul; as ſoon as they were out of the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage inſtead of following the road, they took their way through by-paths and lanes, and ſometimes over the fields, where there was no way at all; this gave an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thinking to our new mourner: they marched thus about two hours, at the end of which they came to a very high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, where there was nothing but woods and precipices, a fit receptacle for none but Bears and Wolves; being entred into the wildeſt and moſt ſecret place of it, the chief turning to his fellows, ſaid with a loud voice, It is now time, Brethren, that we diſmember this body; I, I, ſaid another, this is the fitteſt place in the World for ſuch an operation: our Adventurer was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly aſtoniſhed to hear ſuch a ſentence pronounced, and could not gueſs to what end they had reſolv'd to treat the poor Corps ſo ill; yet ſeeing they did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain themſelves any further to him, he withdrew a little, to ſee what the effect of ſuch a barbarous reſolution would be: He had but juſt gone aſide, when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by their looks and words, that they did not agree about the diviſion of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35775:59"/>and it was not long before from words they came to blows; immediately they all drew ſhort Swords, which they had hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their gowns, (as well the venerable Monks as the reſt) and with them Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols, and being very much animated with their Wine and intereſt, began a very bloody fight. At the noiſe of the Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols going off, the Mules were ſo frighted that they run away, ſnoring and ſtarting as if they had been mad. <hi>Den Diego,</hi> who was not provided for ſuch Company, thought it his beſt courſe to follow the Mules, and endeavour to ſtop them; but they having already got into a narrow lane, hedged in on both ſides, and but juſt wide enough for them and their burden, made it impoſſible for our Adventurer to get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; all that he could do therefore, was to follow them in a very uneven way, ſtumbling ever and anon, and ſometimes falling; having beſides his imagination full of all the horrours of death, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken up with the ſtrange Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſis of his Mourners and Monks, into Souldiers, and of their Breviaries and Beads, into Swords and Piſtols; he could not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently wonder at their inhumanity, to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35775:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>go about to diſmember a perſon of quality, and one whom they were to convey to an honourable reſt; and could not gueſs what new myſteries in burials they would introduce, ſuch as theſe being far from the ordinary rites of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Having run about two Leagues, making of ſuch reflections, juſt as the day began to break, he found he was near a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds little Cottage, where the Mules had ſtop'd of themſelves; the ſhepherd and his boy, warned by the barking of their dogs, came out, and were at the firſt ſight frighted to ſee a man all in black, near a hearſe covered with the ſame ſtuff; but <hi>Don Diego</hi> having approached them, with kind words told them ſuccinctly, that he did convey a dead body, and had loſt his way in the Night, deſiring to be led to the next Village, and promiſing them ſomething for their pains: They imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately contented his deſire, and brought him into a Village hard by, where he met with a venerable Curate, a man of a very good mean, who had formerly liv'd very handſomly in the World, and was now by fortunes injuſtice, or indeed rather by her
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35775:60"/>kindneſs, reduced to live in this ſolitary place, where he paſſed his time in ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and praying, to the great tranquility of his mind; he received <hi>Don Diego</hi> civilly, and afforded him a lodging in his houſe, as well as his dead man one in his Church: It was a great happineſs for our Adventurer to meet with ſuch an hoſt, who could ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently lodge both the living and the dead; as ſoon as he was alone with the Curate, he related to him all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of his Adventure: The Prieſt could not chooſe but admire the ſingularity of it, but was no way able to unriddle the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; he treated <hi>Don Diego</hi> very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly, with good Wine and ſweet Meats, and then put him to bed, where he ſlept till dinner time, and made the <hi>Germans</hi> leap from the bed to the table; there in the midſt of their good chear, the Prieſt diſcovering that <hi>Don Diego</hi> had a great deal of wit, was charmed with his converſation, and deſired him to ſtay one day more, during which time it may be ſome body would come and enquire after the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: <hi>Don Diego,</hi> who knew when he was well, eaſily granted his requeſt, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner they walked out together, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35775:61"/>an extream delight in each others company; but our Adventurer ſoon obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that the Curate had a carriage with him which he had never acquired amongſt his peaſants, took occaſion to intreat his hoſt to let him know by what accident he was brought into ſo ſolitary a place; the Parſon, who was of a very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant humour, without many intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, made him the following relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:35775:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The Story of the Curate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEvil</hi> was the place of my birth, my Father was a Gentleman, more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned by his Virtue than for his Riches, and his principal care of me, was to have me inſtructed in all ſort of learning, that in that at leaſt he might leave me a laſting inheritance; The fame of my capacity in all Sciences, and particularly in the Law, being great, divers very good families de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired my alliance, and offered me their Daughters with conſiderable Fortunes, and no leſs endowments of Beauty and Virtue; but I not being then of a humour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my ſelf, refuſed all their kind prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and liv'd ſo long a Batchelor, that moſt people thought I had contracted ſome ſecret averſion againſt the whole ſex; but I was not ſo happy, as to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with ſo ſtrong an Antidote againſt that paſſion, which was to Poyſon the happineſs of my life; a Lady of incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Beauty and Virtue was at laſt the object of my deſires, in which I proved ſo ſucceſsfull, that ſhe did me the honour to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35775:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>prefer me in her choice to a great many, whoſe fortune and quality might have juſtly attracted her conſent; we were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and I lived two years with her, in a moſt happy union and perfect intelligence: but alas! a moſt horrid ſtorm interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this bleſſed calm, which conſidering the inconſtancy of all this here below, may have been ſaid to have laſted a great while.</p>
               <p>My dear Wife had a Brother, who from a little youthful wildneſs, allowable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in one of his age, became at laſt the moſt debauched and looſe man of all <hi>Sevil;</hi> his diverſions being come to crimes, he fell often into the hands of Juſtice, from whence my induſtry and Money did often reprive him; but he was ſo accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to diſorders of a vicious life, that he could not be without falling into them ſo often, that at laſt he wearied my patience as well as his Siſters, and we both reſolv'd to forbid him my houſe, and leave him to the conduct, or rather giddineſs of his own brain; but alas! my Wife, who had only conſented to uſe her Brother thus out of complaiſance to me, could not continue to perform her part, did ſecretly admit him
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35775:62"/>when I was away, and relieve him in his neceſſity, her good nature not being able to ſee her Brother in diſtreſs, though by his own fault; often coming home on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, I would ſo ſurprize them, that having no better invention, he would hide himſelf behind the hangings, hard by the bed-ſide where we both lay; and becauſe this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention had often ſucceeded, they did free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe it, whenſoever my unexpected ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival did not give him leave to retire. One Night coming home pretty late, I came up ſtaires ſo ſoftly, that they had not heard me, and juſt as I was coming into the Chamber, my Wifes Brother endeavouring to get to his hiding place, entangled his foot in the hangings, and fell with a great noiſe; immediately a furious jealouſie taking poſſeſſion of my breaſt, I flew upon him before he could get up, and unluckily lighting with one hand upon a dagger, which he wore at his girdle, drew it in my paſſion, and ſtruck it deeply into him three or four times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Voice at the wounds he had received, made him known to me, whereupon frighted with the horrour of my fact, I let him riſe, and he having yet ſtrength
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35775:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>enough, and deſirous of revenge, drew his Sword, and in a precipitant manner, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning objects in the dark, made a thruſt which pierced my Wife through the heart, juſt as his out-cry had brought her to his aſſiſtance; they both fell bleeding out their ſouls, and to ſay truth he did as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge himſelf in killing his Siſter, as if he had effected his deſign upon me, for I lived more in her than in my ſelf; my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon the diſmalneſs of our noiſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in with lights, expoſed to my view the perſon that I loved above all the World, juſt fetching her laſt groan; at that, ſeiſed with a moſt violent grief, and reſolving to dye, but not without making ſatisfaction for the enormity of my crime, I ran out of my Houſe, and going to the Judge of Criminal Cauſes, rendred my ſelf his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, deſiring him to proſecute the Law againſt me. This was the laſt act of my reaſon, for a little after I ran mad out of the extremity of ſorrow; upon that the Law ceaſed its purſuit againſt me, and I was put into <hi>Bedlam,</hi> where for ſeven years together I was the object of ſcorn and deriſion of every body who came to ſee the place: At the end of that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35775:63"/>time, by a ſingular providence, I came to my ſelf again, and my Friends with much ado, and more money, got my pardon from Court, and my liberty; but I found my ſelf without any eſtate, it having all been ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred during my diſtraction; much about that time an antient Uncle of mine enjoyed this ſmall Benefice you ſee here, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my condition, reſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d it to me a little before his death; I for my part ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alwaies had an inclination to Books and learning, imbraced voluntarily this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary innocent ſort of life, paſſing with tranquility the reſt of thoſe dayes, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of which have been troubled with ſo great ſtorms.</p>
               <p>Juſt as the Prieſt made an end of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, the Sun took leave of the Earth, and made them do the like of the fountain, and retire to the Village; as ſoon as they came near the Church, they found it open, which being ſomething extraordinary, the Curate went in, followed by <hi>Don Diego,</hi> and found in it a great number of mourners, who had juſt then brought thither the dead body of the Lord of the Mannor; and they were in great conteſt with the Vicar, becauſe they had found in the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35775:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chauncell a ſtrange body, it being a place which belonged only to the Lord of the Mannor: the Curate appeaſed them, and <hi>Don Diego</hi> coming up, and being ſomewhat concerned that his dead man ſhould not be able to find reſt any where, bethought himſelf of a ſtratagem to hinder their throwing him out of the Church, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired they would give him ſome dayes time, in which he hoped to prove, that his dead body had a relation to that of their Lord; he did this only becauſe he ſuppoſed the mourners would be gone the next day, and ſo leave him the liberty of burying the Corps: In the mean time, the Parſon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving enquired into the cauſe of the ſudden death of his Patron, was told that it had proceeded from a great grief, which he took for the loſs of two thouſand Ducats, which ſome thieves at <hi>Madrid</hi> had rob'd him of in the Night, four dayes ago: This was the ſame robbery for the diſcovering of which the <hi>Alguaſil,</hi> which <hi>Don Diego</hi> had met with in his Inn, was going poſt; and indeed the diligence of the dead Lords Heirs was ſuch, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſpatched people on all hands upon the inquiry, ſome of them at laſt met at
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35775:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>the entry of a Wood with a fellow, whom for his ſuſpicious looks they ſeiſed upon and ſearched; they found his pockets full of pick-locks, and ſuch other inſtruments, whereupon they immediately brought him before the Judge of the Village where <hi>Don Diego</hi> was; there for fear of being rack'd, he confeſſed all as followeth.</p>
               <p>That he had been with ſeven more aſſiſtant at a great robbery committed at <hi>Madrid;</hi> that to tranſport their prey the more ſecurely, they had diſguiſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Monks and Mourners, and had buried their prize in a hearſe, which they had loaded upon two Mules, and attended it as if it had been a dead body; that by the help of this invention, they had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all Guards, and avoided all ſearches; that they had reſted themſelves at a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, where he had unluckily taken too much Wine, and was left a ſleep by his Camerades, who had taken his Mourning and given it to another, whom they had hired; that as ſoon as he was awake, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place they were going to, he had followed them, and that he was much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized at his arrival to find two of them dead, and the reſt lye wounded upon the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35775:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>ground, in little hopes of life; that all that he could get from them was, that during their conflict the Stranger whom they had hired was run away with their Mules, and their booty; and that he was taken by them, as he was endeavouring to find out the trace of the Mules.</p>
               <p>By this ample declaration, the Judge came to know that that was the robbery which had precipitated the old Lord in to his Grave, and immediately ſent for the Curate and <hi>Don Diego,</hi> to acquaint them with it; great was their admiration, they go immediately to the Chauncell, where were the two bodies, the one of the Lord, and the other of his treaſure; it was opened in preſence of witneſſes, and found entire; they ſent poſt to the Heir, who came tranſported with joy to view the truth of ſo good tidings; he forgave the poor thief who had revealed, &amp; made the Jaylor let him make his eſcape. The next effect of his gratitude, was to <hi>Don Diego,</hi> whom he would have preſented very handſomly; but he who was noble and generous, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed all other teſtimonies of his kindneſs, beſides the honour of his Frindſhip: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he preſented his Curate with the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35775:65"/>two Mules, and ſo took leave, carrying along with him the richeſt of the two dead bodies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego</hi> after this would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken leave of the Curate, but could not get away; his intreaties to ſtay being ſo cordial, and his converſation ſo good, he ſtayed with him eight day es, diſcourſing with him of the vanities of the World, and the Soveraign happineſs, or <hi>ſummum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> of mankind, which they ſetled in a tranquil contempt for the pleaſures of this life.</p>
               <p>The day of his depart came at laſt, and though he would have excuſed himſelf with many Complements, from taking one of the Mules which the Curate offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, it was not in his power to do it, but engaged in requital to keep a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual correſpondency with this honeſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and divert his ſolitude ſometimes with the news of the Court: Our Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer having thus taken his leave, was ſpurr'd with a deſire of being at <hi>Madrid,</hi> which made him infuſe the like paſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Mule, whoſe legs were better than thoſe of that other, whoſe wearineſs had brought him into all this Adventure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:35775:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Adventure the ninth.</head>
               <p>IT would have been very neceſſary for <hi>Don Diego,</hi> to have ſtayed a little long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with this venerable Church-man, for it may be his converſation in time might have reformed ſomething of the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy of his cuſtoms: As ſoon as ever he came to <hi>Madrid,</hi> he ſent word of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival to all his Camerades, deſiring them to meet him at the old Club, which was at a Tavern where the beſt Wine was ſold: Eight of this mad gang failed not at the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, and there having renewed their acquaintance, and confirmed their League by ſome Bachuick Ceremonies, they all walked out with their Guittars; after ſome Serenades given to their reſpective Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, they ſtopped before an Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries door, whom they reſolved to make the ſubject of that Nights entertainment: It was <hi>Don Diego</hi> that did bear him a ſpight, ever ſince the great diſeaſe he had when <hi>Leander</hi> dyed, and his Wife turned Nun; for this Apothecary being <hi>Diego's</hi> Neighbour, had out of malice ſeeing that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35775:66"/>our Adventurer did not make uſe of him, cauſed his Prentices to make ſuch a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable noiſe upon two braſs Mortars all day long, that it was impoſſible for <hi>Don Diego</hi> to ſleep; his intreaties and prayers had ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified nothing towards the ſilencing of the Mortars, for he was ſtill anſwered, that he muſt follow his Trade, and that Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or <hi>Don Diego</hi> would not keep him and his family, if they ſhould neglect their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to let him enjoy his reſt; ſo that at laſt he was fain to fine for ſilence for a fortnight, at a pretty round rate, and that at the end of his diſeaſe too, having ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much before by that troubleſome chiming. All this conſidered, and by our Adventurer related to the Company, inflamed them, who were already heated with Wine, to a deſire of revenge; but <hi>Diego</hi> who was chiefly concerned, reſolved alſo to be the main actor, and advancing to the door, bounced at it as if he would have beat it down; the Apothecary who was juſt got to bed, was loath to riſe, but anſwering from his bed, began the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Dialogue with <hi>Don Diego,</hi> affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill a little Latin in it, to ſhew he had enough to underſtand the Doctors bill.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:35775:67"/>The Apothecary.</p>
               <p>Who's that that knocks ſo haſtily <hi>ad Portam meam?</hi> either they are inſipid fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, or worſhipfull Conſtable, for none elſe durſt be ſo bold at this time of the Night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray Sir does not there live hereabouts a certain half Doctor, otherwiſe an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary, called <hi>Mr. Robert?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apothecary.</p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Robert</hi> he may be Doctor <hi>Robert omnino</hi> I hope for you; 'tis here he lives, and ſpeaks to you in <hi>propria perſona;</hi> ſpeak without prolixity, what would you have?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas Sir, is it you? I beg your pardon; pray Sir do not abuſe me, if it be you open the door quickly, for I am in great haſte, my poor Friend is a dead Man if you do not aſſiſt him at this very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
               <p>The Apothecary.</p>
               <p>I know you not, neither will I open my door at this time of the Night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good Sir do not neglect the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35775:67"/>the Phyſitian told us he had left his Preſcription here, I hope you have not forgot to make what he order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>The Apothecary.</p>
               <p>Oh! now, <hi>Deo gratias,</hi> I begin to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand you; Is it not for the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Gentleman you mean, who has ſo great a pain in his Stomach?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Diego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I, I, 'tis for him.</p>
               <p>The Apothecary.</p>
               <p>Why is he in ſuch haſte? my Man told me the Phyſitian had ordered only for Thurſday, which is <hi>dies craſtinus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Don Diego.</p>
               <p>For Thurſday! Alas Sir your Man was miſtaken, and it was for to day; if you fail to ſend it, the Gentleman will go near to dye for want of it.</p>
               <p>The Apothecary.</p>
               <p>Friend do not take ſnuff, but have pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience a little and I'le riſe, and within a quarter of an hour the Compoſition ſhall be ready.</p>
               <p>Don Diego.</p>
               <p>Pray Sir make haſte, you know the Gentleman will recompence you well; but
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35775:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>pray have a care of a miſtake; in the mean time I'le go let him know that you are coming.</p>
               <p>At theſe words making as if he had gone away, he only retired to the reſt of the Company, and then drawing ſoftly near the Apothecaries door, he heard him call his man, and gave him theſe orders: Ho, <hi>James,</hi> where is that purge which we made laſt week for the ſick Lawyer, that dyed as I was carrying it to him? take it and carry it to this <hi>Neapolitan,</hi> it will do as well, his diſtemper is the ſame: At theſe words <hi>Diego</hi> was fain to retreat, not being able to keep himſelf from laughing, and having acquainted his Camerades with it, mov'd in them the ſame paſſion; but withall they gave him a thouſand curſes for his damned Compoſition, taking from him a ſtrong averſion againſt that poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning Trade, which is a Plague greater than any Peſtilence, as killing continually all the year round, and that with privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and protection too.</p>
               <p>To ſee what this would end in, they reſolv'd to ſtop at the end of the Street, and dog the Apothecary to the place and perſon who was to be ſo unfortunate as
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:35775:68"/>to be poyſoned for their mirth; they had not ſtayed above half a quarter of an hour, when out comes the Apothecary <hi>ſemi</hi>-Doctor with a glaſs in his hand; they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him one by one, and ſaw him go in to a <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Gentlemans houſe; after a great deal of ſtay he was forc'd to make at the door, for God knows they did not ſit up for him, the Gentleman was one of thoſe crazy people who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes drenching themſelves, and making an Apothecaries Shop of their belly; as for him, though he were really infirm, yet having a falſe opinion of his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, he did continually increaſe them, by fancying them greater than indeed they were; he was very ſuperſtitious in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving punctually his Phyſitians orders, and it ſeems they had ordered him to be purg'd within two or three dayes; he had a <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> upon whoſe care he extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relyed for the adminiſtration of his Medicaments, leaving to him to know the hours, the ſeaſons, the quantities, and all the other little circumſtances upon which ſick people of quality think that all the effect of the remedy depends: The <hi>Valet</hi> hid taken the laſt preſcription from
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:35775:69"/>the Phyſitians, and ſent it to the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary, but finding by it that his Maſter was to take nothing till within two dayes, took that time to go and viſit a young Wench he was in love with; and it fell out unluckily, that our Apothecary brought his admirable Compoſition juſt as the <hi>Valet de Chambre</hi> was gone out; upon that the Maſter believing the Apothecary, who ſaid that ſome body of the houſe had been at his Shop, and ordered him to bring immediately this laxative potion, ſwallowed without more ado this dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous draught.</p>
               <p>In the mean time our Adventurer and his company, having been very merry at the pleaſant effect that their drollery was like to produce, thought they had done enough for this Night, and reſolved to retire to their Lodging, and put off to the next day to enquire into the ſucceſs of the Phyſick which <hi>Don Diego</hi> had preſcrib'd the <hi>Neapolitan:</hi> As they were going home, they perceiv'd they were but ſeven, and that one of the Company was miſſing; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring for him, another who knew his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, told them he was gone about ſome buſineſs in which he needed no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion;
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35775:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>but to ſatisfie the Reader he muſt know,</p>
               <p>That <hi>Robert</hi> the Apothecary had a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pretty daughter, but ſo proud that ſhe deſpiſed all the young Shop-keepers in their quarter, and would receive courtſhip from none but young Gentlemen of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, whom nevertheleſs ſhe made to keep their diſtance, by the Empire of her beauty; <hi>Riodan,</hi> who was this Camerade of <hi>Don Diego's</hi> that was miſſing, had long been a paſſionate Servant to her, and now at laſt by means of the Maid, whom he had corrupted with gifts, had got an aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Miſtreſs, being promiſed to be introduced into her Chamber, when her Father and Mother ſhould be aſleep. He happening that evening to be in the Company of <hi>Don Diego</hi> at Supper, had continued with them, after ſeeing that they went that way whither he himſelf was deſigned; but he was infinitely plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed when he ſaw the ſucceſs of <hi>Diego's</hi> fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, as being the luckieſt thing he could wiſh for; immediately as they followed the Father, he ſtole to the door, and upon his ſignal was let in by the Maid: She led him ſoftly to <hi>Dorothaeas</hi> Lodging, which was
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35775:70"/>upon the ſame floor with her ancient Mothers chamber, and only divided by a Wainſcote ſeparation; As ſoon as he came into the room, ſhe roſe up as it were ſurpriz'd, and being half undreſſed, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to the paſſionate <hi>Riodan</hi> ſuch love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly breaſts, and ſo fine a skin, that he could no longer keep the reſpect he was wont to have for her, but embracing her in his arms, began to paſs on to a further privacy; the Lady, who was no fool, knowing the conſequence of ſuch an action, thruſt him back with a kind of coldneſs, and told him he was miſtaken if he thought to enjoy her otherwiſe than his Wife. <hi>Riodan</hi> could do no other than approve of her virtuous reſolution, and offered to give any aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his fidelity, that ſuch a time and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion would admit of; that if ſhe would be content with a promiſe of Marriage under his hand, he would give it her immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>Dorothaea</hi> who had a kindneſs for him, thought that a ſufficient engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from a perſon of quality, and bid her Maid give him paper and pen and ink to write it: She did, and he having writ a very fair one, and ſhewed it to <hi>Dorothaea,</hi> was going to ſign it, when unluckly
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35775:70"/>with his elbow he overthrew the ſtandiſh, which was a great leaden one, and ſtood upon the end of the Table; it fell upon a braſs Mortar, and made ſuch a noiſe, that <hi>Dorothaea's</hi> Mother ſtarted up out of her ſleep, and cryed, who's there? not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwered by the two Lovers, who were as it were thunder-ſtruck, ſhe with much ado crawled out of her bed, and was coming to her Daughters chamber, in which ſhe ſaw a light: <hi>Dorothaea</hi> miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome ſuch thing, and not knowing where to hide <hi>Riodan,</hi> had with much ado prevailed upon him to go away, and was juſt thruſting him haſtily out of her chamber, as her Mother was in the entry coming into it; they both met full butt, and the old Woman being weak, fell down with the knock, crying murder, murder, while <hi>Riodan</hi> ſtumbling over her got away; the Daughter mightily fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her Mothers outcry, and not knowing what to do, nor how to ſhelter her ſelf from her Fathers anger, when he ſhould come home, ran after <hi>Riodan,</hi> and having overtaken him in the Street, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to carry her away and protect her, relying entirely upon his generoſity: The
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:35775:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>Maid who had been the mediatrix of their loves, leaving her old Miſtreſs upon the ground calling out for help, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the two Lovers; at laſt at the old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans deſolate cries, ſome Neighbours heard her, and came in; they ſearched all the houſe, but found no body.</p>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Dorothaea's</hi> Father, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left his damnable Medicine in the <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> Gentlemans body, comes home, and finds all in deſolation; his Wife almoſt dead, his Daughter run away, and no body able to tell why, or with whom: Great was his amazement, but greater his rage, when he came to himſelf; but let us leave him a little, and ſee what effect the Phyſick wrought.</p>
               <p>The Potion being old, made of ill Drugs, and given out of time, and upon a full Stomach, the Gentleman having Supp'd a little before, it made him moſt horrid ſick, giving him gripes which made him often cry, <hi>oime queſto cane tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditore ma amazzato:</hi> He paſſed a whole Night in theſe pangs, and in the morning his <hi>Valet de Chambre</hi> being come in, he reproached him with being the cauſe of his death, in bidding the Apothecary give
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:35775:71"/>him Phyſick ſo out of ſeaſon; the <hi>Valet</hi> very innocent, ſwears and proteſts that he never was there, and that the diſorder did proceed either from the ignorance or malice of the Apothecary, who he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved had done this of his own head, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their pragmatical cuſtom; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately he runs to the Phyſitian, and brings him along with him to ſee his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; the Phyſitian being come, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving felt the ſick mans pulſe, grew very angry, ſaying, the Apothecary was a Knave; immediately he gave the Patient ſome excellent Cordials, which were a pretty good Antidote againſt the venom of this Poyſon: That done, he has the Apothecary cited before the Faculty of Phyſitians, to anſwer for his ſawcineſs and ignorance, in giving Phyſick of his own head. Now let us return to him. Having a little aſſwaged his paſſion, the firſt thing he reſolved, was to beſtirr himſelf gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly for the reparation of his honour, and to be revenged of him that had thus affronted him: Having long conſidered and ruminated with himſelf, who it might be that had carried away his Daughter, he could find his conjectures upon none
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:35775:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>more probably as he thought, than upon <hi>Agrimont,</hi> the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Gentlemans <hi>Valet de Chambre;</hi> he was a ſpruce young idle fellow, that uſed alwayes when he came to his houſe, to be ſaying ſome oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thing or other to his Daughter; to which ſhe anſwering merrily, he thought might have obliged him to have framed this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise; and that the better to effect it, he had made him riſe and carry the Medicine, employing on that errand ſome other of his fellow ſervants, while he himſelf was got in to his Daughter. Thus prepoſſeſs'd, he goes to the Criminal Judge, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his complaint, gets a Warrant and Officers to arreſt and impriſon <hi>Agrimont</hi> for a rape: Maſter <hi>Robert</hi> having this, made ſuch diligence, and feed ſo well the Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poles, that they ſeiſed my <hi>Valet de Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre</hi> in a few hours, and hurried him away to Priſon: But almoſt at the ſame time, by an order from the Faculty of Phyſitians, he was arreſted, and brought before them, to give an account for his giving the <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> Phyſick without order; out of which difficulty not being able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intangle himſelf, and taking it to be only a trick of the <hi>Neapolitan,</hi> to hinder the purſuit
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:35775:72"/>againſt his <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> he was ſo perplex'd that he fell ſick of a very violent burning Feaver. <hi>Agrimont</hi> in the mean time, ſeeing himſelf clapped up upon a falſe accuſation, for having ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed a young Woman whom he had not ſeen, was in a great rage at the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary, and did by Letters incite his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who loved him, to take a ſignal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon poor <hi>Robert;</hi> they were four whole dayes in theſe perplexities and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, like to dye, or run mad: By that time <hi>Riordan,</hi> the true <hi>Paris</hi> of this <hi>Hele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> had very generouſly Married her at a little Village, about two Leagues off; and being advertiſed by a Friend of the horrid diſorder that was amongſt ſo many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for his ſake, came to the Town with his Wife, and having firſt writ a comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Apothecary, in which he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him Father, promiſing him to love his Daughter as his Wife, he went to ſee him; great was the joy of our poor Maſter <hi>Robert,</hi> at this good news; he embraced his Son-in-Law, made a great ſatisfaction and reparation to <hi>Agrimont,</hi> for the injury he had done him; and as for the Potion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out of time, his Son-in-Law having
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:35775:73"/>been one of that Club, told him all theſtory of it, confirming the like to the Phyſitians, who elſe were ready to have fined him.</p>
               <p>The Apothecary would fain have had an action againſt <hi>Don Diego,</hi> but <hi>Riodan</hi> being unwilling to ſee his Friend in trouble, hindred <hi>Roberts</hi> purſuit againſt our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer; yet the Judge coming to hear the ſtory, and having beſides a relation given him of <hi>Don Diego's</hi> extravagant life, ſent for him, and by publick ſentence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to live as other people did, binding him in a good ſum of Money to retire to his lodging by ten of the Clock in Summer, and by nine in Winter, at the lateſt.</p>
               <p>He was forced to ſubmit, to his great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, and obſerves to this day that ſevere order, which put an end to all his Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as it muſt (Reader) to your curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, till he break it, and give us matter to make a ſecond volume of his Life.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="story">
            <pb facs="tcp:35775:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE MARRIAGE OF Belphegor.</head>
            <head type="sub">An <hi>ITALIAN</hi> Novel, Tranſlated from <hi>Machiavel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is recorded in the ancient Chronicles of <hi>Florence,</hi> that a certain holy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe life was the admiration of that age, falling one day into a Trance, had a very ſtrange apparition: It ſeem'd to him, that the Souls of Married Men that came trooping in great numbers to Hell, cried out all of them as they paſs'd,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35775:74"/>that their Marriage was the cauſe of their Miſery, and their Wives the occaſion of their coming thither: <hi>Minos Radamanth,</hi> and the whole infernal Privy-Council, were amazed at the clamour; at firſt they could not believe there was any thing in the buſineſs, but at laſt obſerving the ſame complaints continually multiplyed, they thought it fit to make <hi>Pluto</hi> acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Pluto</hi> underſtanding the report, without imparting any thing to his Wife, (who had taken Phyſick that Week, and kept her Chamber) reſolv'd the matter ſhould be accurately examin'd, and ſuch courſe be taken, as was likelieſt to make the ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſcovery of the truth: He iſſu'd out his Writs immediately, and aſſembled his Courts; his Princes, Dukes, Counts, and Barons, were all preſent; never was Senate ſo full, nor never was affair of that importance before it: The holy Father that beheld all, affirms poſitively, that <hi>Pluto</hi> delivered himſelf in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Right Truſty and well-Beloved,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though our Kingdom was aſſigned us from Heaven, and the fatal decree has anciently determined our Dominion: Though that
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35775:74"/>ſentence be irrevocable, and above the cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of any Humane Power; yet ſeeing his prudence is moſt ſafe, that is dictated by Laws, and his judgement moſt ſolid, that is fortified with others, We are reſolvd to take your Counſels along with us, which way we are to ſteer in an affair, that otherwiſe may prove (in time) of great diſhonour to our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Souls of married Men, that are continually flocking into our Dominions, do unanimouſly exclaim againſt their Wives, as the only perſons that ſend them tumbling hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to us it ſeems impoſſible: yet for aſ much as a peremptory and determinate ſentence upon their bare allegations, would not ſuit with our Satanical Mercy; ſo a careleſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſsion on the other ſide, could not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reflection on our Juſtice: That mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſuch importance therefore may have their due diſquiſition, and Our adminiſtration be defended from obloquy or ſcandal, that no inconvenieny may follow for want of delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that ſome better expedient may be found out, than our ſelves have happily thought on, We have thought good to call you together, being confident and aſſured by the aſſiſtance of your Counſels, the Honour and Reputation of our Empire will be continued
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35775:75"/>as unqueſtionable for the future, as it has been preſerved hitherto, by our own proper care ſolicitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was not one preſent, but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged it a buſineſs of importance, and well worthy an exact conſideration: It was the opinion of the whole Board, that all imaginable means was to be uſed to find out the truth, but what means that was, could not be agreed on; ſome were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, a ſingle perſon was to be diſpatcht into this World, and no more; others judged it better to ſend ſeveral, and that the diſcovery would be more certain from the experience of many, than of one; a third ſort, more brisk and ſevere in their Counſels, thought that clutter unneceſſary, and that clapping good ſtore of them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the rack, would be enough doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to extort a confeſſion. However it was at laſt carried by the plurality of Voices, that a ſingle perſon only ſhould be ſent, and in this reſolution the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany acquieſc'd: Nevertheleſs there being no body found that would voluntarily undertake the imployment, it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the election ſhould be by lot; and at the ſame time, having made their bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:35775:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſhuffled them, the lot fell upon <hi>Belphegor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One may ſay, and ſay true, that fortune never decided any thing ſo juſtly; for <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phegor</hi> was no ordinary Devil, and <hi>Pluto</hi> having made him formerly Generaliſſimo of his Armies, 'tis to be preſumed he was no Novice; for all this he had a Months mind to be quit of his embaſſie; but the order being unalterable, he was forc'd to ſubmit, and accept theſe conditions that were ſolemnly decreed, <hi>That a hundred thouſand Ducats ſhould be paid him immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, to defray the expences of his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; That he ſhould aſſume the ſhape of a Man; That he ſhould take a Woman to his wedded Wife, and live with her (if poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) ten years; that at the end of the term, (pretending to die) he ſhould give her the ſlip, repair immediately to his old quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and make affidavit upon his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of all the pleaſures and calamities of Matrimony.</hi> It was declared to him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that during this Metamorphoſis, he was to be ſubject to the pains and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of Humanity, as ſickneſs, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and poverty: But that if by his cunning or dexterity he could diſintangle
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:35775:76"/>himſelf, it ſhould be allowed him, and not imputed as any ſcandal or reproach. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phegor</hi> accepts the conditions, receives his Ducats, and having drawn a ſpruce party of horſe out of his Guards, and furniſh'd himſelf with Pages and Footmen good ſtore, he ſet out immediately for this World, and arrived at <hi>Florence</hi> in a very fair equipage: He choſe that place above all other, for the conveniency of improving his Moneys, and putting it to intereſt with greater advantage. He called himſelf <hi>Don Roderick of Caſtile;</hi> he took a very noble Houſe in the Fauxburg of <hi>All-Saints;</hi> and that his quality might be undiſcovered, he gave out that he was a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that being young he took a Voyage into <hi>Syria,</hi> that he had dwelt ſome time in <hi>Aleppo,</hi> where he had got moſt part of his Eſtate; but being weary there, he was come into <hi>Italy,</hi> as a Country more agreeable with his humour, with intention (if any fair opportunity was offered) to Marry: <hi>Don Roderick</hi> ſeemed to be a very handſome Man, about thirty years of age; and in ſhort time after his arrival, he made it evident enough that he was rich, and by his liberality, that he knew how to make
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:35775:76"/>the beſt uſe of them; inſomuch as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Gentlemen of <hi>Florence,</hi> that had more Daughters than Money, took all poſſible pains to inſinuate how welcome he ſhould be into their Alliance. <hi>Don Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> that had choice of Miſtreſſes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd one that was tranſcendently hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome before them all; the ſtory ſayes, ſhe was called <hi>Honeſta,</hi> and was the Daughter of <hi>Americ Donati,</hi> who had three more alſo to Marry, and three Sons between twenty or twenty five years of age: But though <hi>Seignur Americ</hi> was of one of the nobleſt Families of <hi>Florence,</hi> yet he was look'd upon as down the winde, and one that was overlaid with too many Children, and the unavoidable charges of his Nobility: But <hi>Don Roderick</hi> took an order for that, defraying the whole expence of his Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; out of his own purſe managing all things with that ſplendor and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, that there was nothing omitted that was deſirable upon ſuch an occaſion. It was mentioned before, as out of the conditions propoſed to <hi>Belphegor,</hi> that as ſoon as he was out of the Infernal Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, he ſhould be ſubject to all the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mankind; and accordingly he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35775:77"/>immediately to take delight in the Honours and Gallantry of the World; and as cunning a Devil as he was, to be whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled with the flatteries and applauſes of Men: But that which delighted him ſo much, coſt him dear; beſides that he had not been long with <hi>Honeſta,</hi> but he fell ſtark mad in love with her, and finding ſomething or other extraordinary in her, that I cannot think of, he was ſo far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured, he never thought himſelf hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py before; inſomuch as when ſhe was me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, or out of humour, he would curſe his Commiſſion, and take his corporal Oath his very life was tedious. On the otherſide it is not to be forgot, that <hi>Honeſta</hi> marrying <hi>Roderick,</hi> and bringing him Beauty and Nobility inſtead of a Portion, ſhe thought it not fit to leave her pride and untractableneſs behind her; theſe two good qualities were ſo eminently in her, that <hi>Roderick</hi> who had been uſed to <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers,</hi> and had more than once had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of it, ſwore point Blank his Wives inſolence was beyond it: For when ſhe once found the fondneſs and paſſion her Husband had for her, believing ſhe could manage him with a Switch, and order him
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:35775:77"/>as ſhe pleaſed, ſhe carried her ſelf like his Soveraign, and handled him without pity or reſpect; and if it hapned he denied her any thing, ſhe gave him immediately to underſtand, that ſhe was alſo as eloquent in ſcoulding, as others of her quality. By this you may judge what a cooler this was to <hi>Don Roderick:</hi> Nevertheleſs the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his Father-in-Law, his Wifes Brothers, the Kindred he had by that bleſſed Marriage, but above all the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and tenderneſs he had for her, made him endure all patiently. I ſhall not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the expence of his Cloaths, which though never ſorich, he was forc'd to change every week, according to the ordinary va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Ladies in <hi>Florence.</hi> Beſides theſe there were other things, were of noleſs inconvenience; he was forc'd (to preſerve the peace) to aſſiſt his Father-in-Law in the Marriage of his other Daughters, which coſt him a good round ſum: Moreover that all things might go well, and his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency continue with his Conſort, he was glad to ſend one of her Brothers into the <hi>Levant</hi> with wollen Stuffs, another into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> with Silks, and to furniſh the third with wherewithall to ſet
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35775:78"/>up a Goldſmiths-ſhop in <hi>Florence:</hi> All which afflictions together were ſufficient to diſcompoſe any Devil of a thouſand, yet he had other thrown into the bargain: There is not any Town all <hi>Italy</hi> more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant in their expences, in their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nival and Feaſts of <hi>St. John,</hi> than <hi>Florence:</hi> And <hi>Honeſta</hi> upon that occaſion, muſt needs have her <hi>Roderick</hi> out do all people of his Rank, in the ſumptuouſneſs of his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, in the magnificence of his Balls, and other divertiſements that are uſual at thoſe times: He ſuffered all theſe calamities, for the ſame reaſons he endured the reſt; and though perhaps theſe difficulties were very hard and unpleaſant, he would have thought them ſupportable, could he have been ſatisfied his patience would have procured any quietneſs in his Family, and that he might have peaceably attended the hour of his diſtruction. But <hi>Don Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> found the clear contrary; beſides the expence you have heard ſhe occaſioned, her inſolence was accompanied with a thouſand other inconveniencies, inſomuch as he could keep neither officer nor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in his houſe, above three dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. This was a ſevere trouble to him,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:35775:78"/>to find it was impoſſible for him to keep any body about him, though never ſo well experienc'd or affected to his affairs: Nor indeed could any body blame them for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their leaves, when the Devils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that he brought along with him, did chooſe rather to return, and toaſt the bottoms of their feet againſt the fire of Hell, than live in this World under the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſo ſuper-deviliſh a Woman. <hi>Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks</hi> life being thus miſerably uncomfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and his ſtock that he had reſerved, exhauſted by her extravagant expences, he was reduced to that paſs, he ſubſiſted only upon the hopes of the advantage he ſhould make, by the return of ſome Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels he had ſent into the Eaſt and Weſt. And whereas before he had very good credit in that Town, to continue it and keep up his Port, he borrowed Money of ſuch as are uſed in that place to put it out; but thoſe kind of people being ſuch, as are not uſually ſleepy or negligent in their affairs, they took notice immediately he was not over-punctual to his day: His purſe being already empty, and he reduc'd to the higheſt extremity, at one daſh he receives news of two as diſaſterous acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:35775:79"/>as could poſſibly befall him. The firſt was, that one of <hi>Honeſtas</hi> Brothers had loſt at Hazzard all that <hi>Roderick</hi> had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted in his hands; and the other was no more welcome, which was, that his other Brother-in-Law returning into <hi>Italy,</hi> was himſelf caſt away, and all his goods. The buſineſs was no ſooner known in <hi>Florence,</hi> but his Creditors had a meeting, where giving him over for one that was irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably loſt, and not daring to diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, becauſe the time of payment was not yet come, they concluded he was to be watcht very cloſe, leſt he ſhould chouſe them, and ſhew them a light pair of heels. <hi>Don Roderick of Caſtile</hi> on the other ſide, conſidering with himſelf his affairs were paſt remedy, and alſo the terms he was obliged to by the infernal Law, reſolves to take horſe and be gone without more ado, which he performed without much difficulty, living conveniently for that by the Port <hi>del Prato:</hi> yet he was no ſooner marcht off, but the alarm was taken by his Creditors; they repair immediately to the Magiſtrates, and purſue him not only with Poſt and Officers, but leſt a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number of Ducats ſhould debauch
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:35775:79"/>that kind of Cattle, who are no better in <hi>Italy</hi> than other places, and prevail with them for an abatement of their ſpeed, they follow him themſelves in a full body, with impatience of hearing ſome tydings of him, <hi>Roderick</hi> in the mean time was no fool, but conſidered very well what he had to do; as ſoon as he was gallop'd about half a league from the Town, he leaves the high way, and his horſe with it (the Country being incloſed and full of ditches on both ſides) and was forced to make the reſt of his journey on foot, which he did very ſucceſsfully; for wandring up and down under the ſhelter of the Vines and Reeds, that abound much in thoſe parts, he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at laſt at <hi>Peretola,</hi> at the houſe of <hi>Jean Matteo del Bricca,</hi> Baily to <hi>Jean del Bene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By very good fortune, he meets <hi>Matteo</hi> carrying fodder to his Cattle; he accoſts him immediately, and promiſes him as he was a Gentleman, that if he would deliver him from the Catchpoles that were in purſuit of him, with deſign to clap him up and ſtarve him in Priſon, he had an inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his pate would make him rich out of hand, and of this he would give ſuch
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:35775:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>evidence before he departed, as ſhould aſſure him of his truth and fidelity; and if I do not, ſayes he, with a damn'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation, I will be content to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up into their clutches that perſecute me. Now you muſt underſtand, that though <hi>Matteo</hi> was a Hinde and a Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, yet the fellow had cunning enough, and knew on which ſide his bread was buttered; he conſidered, if he undertook him and miſcarryed, he had nothing to loſe; and that if he ſucceeded, he ſhould be made for ever; without any more ado therefore he promiſes him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and clapping him cloſe upon a dunghill that was before the gate, he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him over with bruſh-faggots and reeds, and ſuch other fewel as lay there in readineſs for the fire: And indeed he was no ſooner in his retirements, but in came the Creditors with full cry; they ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered and laid about them like Lords, but all to no purpoſe, <hi>Matteo</hi> could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to confeſs ſo much as that he ſaw him; inſomuch as marching on ſtill in the purſuit, but with as little ſucceſs as they came thither, they gave <hi>Roderick</hi> and their Money over for loſt, and returned to <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:35775:80"/>every jot as wiſe as they were before: The Coaſt being clear in this manner, and the alarm over, <hi>Matteo</hi> ſteals to the cloſet where he had left <hi>Roderick,</hi> gives him a little freſh air, and conjures him to be as good as his word: <hi>Roderick</hi> was very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in that point, and I dare ſay never any Devil, as to matters of gratitude, had more of a Gentleman; he gave him thanks for the great obligation he had received; he ſwore over and over again, he would do whatever lay in his power to diſcharge himſelf of his promiſe, and in the heat and height of his complements, to convince him that he meant as he ſaid, he gives him the whole ſtory as you have had it, and at laſt told him the very way that he had pitch'd upon to make him a Prince: Know then, ſayes he, that whenever you hear of any Lady that is poſſeſs'd, 'tis no other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil but I that have poſſeſs'd her; and be ſure I will never leave her, till you come your ſelf and force me from my quarters, after which you have wit enough to make your own terms for your payment. They had very few words more, he only gave him the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet once or twice, and ſhewed him two or three jugling tricks, and vaniſh'd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:35775:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>A while after there was a great noiſe about the Town, that <hi>Meſ. Ambroſio Amideis</hi> Daughter, that was Married to <hi>Bonaculo Thebald<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cci's</hi> Son, was poſſeſs'd; her Father and Mother did not fall to uſe all the remedles are uſual in ſo deplorable a caſe; they brought before her <hi>St. Zanobes</hi> Head, and <hi>St. J. Galberts</hi> Cloak, which was nuts to <hi>Belphegor,</hi> and made him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but laugh: There was no body in her but <hi>Don Roderick de Caſtile,</hi> who was as ingenious a Gentleman-devil as one would wiſh, and that the world might take notice that this was no fantaſtick imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor fit of the Night-mare, nor any ſuch trifle, but that ſhe was really poſſeſs'd, ſhe ſpake Latin better than <hi>Tully</hi> ever Writ, diſputed in Philoſophy, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the ſecrets and ſins of ſeveral people that were there, who were very much ſurpriz'd to find the Devil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern himſelf with thoſe kind of affairs.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt there was one holy Father he did a great diſcourteſie to, in blurring out before the whole company, as if he had kept a young Laſs four years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his Cell, in the habit of a young Monk; and after all this, let any body
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:35775:81"/>judge whether the poſſeſſion was not like to be true; <hi>Ambroſio</hi> in the mean time was in great affliction for his Daughter; he had tryed all the wayes that Phyſick or Religion could propoſe, but to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; ſo as he was brought to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt point of deſpair, when <hi>Matteo</hi> came to him, and undertook the cure of his Daughter, if he would give him five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Florins,</hi> which he deſigned to lay out in Land at <hi>Peretola:</hi> In ſhort, <hi>Matteo</hi> was an honeſt fellow, and would have done the miracle <hi>gratis,</hi> and like a Gentleman, but his pockets were hollow, and he had great oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for Money at that time; Seignior <hi>Ambroſio</hi> accepts the conditions, and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teo</hi> falls to work; he began very civilly with certain Maſſes and other Ceremonies, that he might appear the more formal in the buſineſs; at length he ſtole to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ear, calls <hi>Roderick,</hi> and tells him he was come thither to him, and did require him to be as good as his word. Content ſays <hi>Roderick,</hi> and that you may ſee I ſhall deal with you like a perſon of quality, take notice, that becauſe this expedition is not enough to inrich you, and do your buſineſs, I will befriend you more than
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:35775:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>once, for which reaſon as ſoon as I am departed from hence, away I'le march into the Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and don't fear but I'le ſtick to her, till you come to exerciſe me, ſo as there you may make up your markets at a blow, &amp; become conſiderable for ever: but be ſure after that I be troubled with you no more; and as ſoon as he had ſaid ſo, whip ſays he out of the Lady, and was gone to the great joy and aſtoniſhment of the whole Town.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Belphegor</hi> in the mean time was as good as his word, as he promiſed <hi>Matteo;</hi> away he goes, and in two or three days time it was all over <hi>Italy,</hi> that the Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> was in the ſame condition; which was good news for <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teo,</hi> who was at this bout to gain the Philoſophers-ſtone: In ſhort, he tryed all means poſſible; the Monks went to work with their prayers, and their croſſes, but to no purpoſe; The Devil would not budge till <hi>Matteo</hi> came himſelf, who had formerly oblig'd him. The King had news of what had happened at <hi>Florence,</hi> and ſends away immediately for <hi>Matteo</hi> to his Court; who came accordingly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome few ceremonious formalities, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:35775:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>for concealment of the myſtery, he cures his daughter. However <hi>Roderick</hi> before his departure, as is reported in the Chronicle, accoſted hint in this manner. You ſee, <hi>Matteo,</hi> I have been as good as my word; you ſee you are become rich in a trice, and may take your eaſe for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo as if I be not miſtaken, I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged my ſelf as to you very honeſtly, hereafter have a care how you come near me; for as hitherto I have done you knights-ſervice, henceforward I will do you as much miſchief as I can. <hi>Matteo</hi> being returned to <hi>Florence</hi> very wealthy, (for the king of <hi>Naples</hi> had given him above five thouſand Ducats) he thought of nothing now but injoying that peaceably he had got, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver imagining <hi>Roderick</hi> would do him any harm; but his deſigns were much fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a report out of <hi>France,</hi> that <hi>Lewis</hi> the ſevenths Daughter was poſſeſs'd as the former: <hi>Matteo</hi> was in great trouble, on the one ſide he was not ignorant of the power of that Prince, on the other he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred <hi>Rodericks</hi> laſt words; the King uſed all means poſſible, but without any ſucceſs; he was told what feats <hi>Matteo</hi> had done, and diſpatch'd a Poſt to him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:35775:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>to deſire his Company at <hi>Paris;</hi> but <hi>Matteo</hi> pretending I know not what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſitions, that rendred him incapable of ſerving his Majeſty, the King was forc'd to write to the Magiſtrates, who ſent away <hi>Matteo</hi> immediately.</p>
            <p>Being arrived at <hi>Paris,</hi> he was in great affliction, becauſe he knew not which way for his life to perform what was expected from him. At laſt he goes to the King, and tells him, that true it was indeed, he had formerly wrought ſome cures in that kind, but that it was not in reaſon to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he could diſpoſſeſs all people he met with, ſeeing there were ſome Devils ſo refractory and croſs-grain'd, neither threats nor enchantments, nor devotion it ſelf would do no good on: That he ſaid not this out of any repugnancy or unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to do as he was deſired, but that in caſe his endeavours were ineffectual, he might have his Majeſties pardon. The King was ſtark mad at the ſtory, and told him in plain terms, if he did not rout the Devil out of his Daughter, as he had done out of others, he would hang him forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; for he ſaw no reaſon why Miracles were not as feaſible at <hi>Paris,</hi> as at <hi>Florence</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:35775:83"/>and <hi>Naples:</hi> Theſe words toucht <hi>Matteo</hi> to the quick, he thought there was no pleaſure to be taken in being hang'd in that manner, and that what the King had ſaid, was without any equivocation: However he recollected himſelf a little, or at leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo, and calling for the Princeſs that was poſſeſs'd, he makes his approaches, and whiſpering her in the ear, told <hi>Roderick</hi> he was his very humble ſervant, and put him in minde of the good office he had done him, when he delivered him out of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons of the Law; adding withall, that if he leſt him in the lurch, in the extremity of danger he was then in, the whole World would cry out on his ingratitude; <hi>Roderick</hi> heard him with no more patience than needs muſt, he ſwaggers, ſwears, ſtorms, and layes about like a Devil in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, gives him a thouſand and a thouſand ill words, but they could diſtinguiſh only theſe few at the laſt: How now, you Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Traitor, have you the impudence to come near me again? have you forgot it was I that made you fortune? but I'le make all the World ſee, and you too, with a pox to you, that I can take away as well as give; beſides which, you ſhall not
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:35775:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>fail to be hang'd before you get away from <hi>Paris:</hi> Poor <hi>Matteo</hi> ſeeing no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for his misfortunes, he fell a think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome other way, and having ſent back the Lady to her Chamber, he made this ſpeech to the King. Sir, I have told you before, that there are certain ill-natur'd capricious Spirits, one knows not which way to deal withall, and of this ſort is that which poſſeſſes your Daughter; if what we ſhall adminiſter might be ſufficient, your Majeſty ſhould be happy in your deſires, and mine alſo; but if things prove other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and your Majeſty be not ſatisfied with my endeavours, I ſhall ſubmit, and your Majeſty may deal with me as I deſerve: In the mean time, I deſire your Majeſty would give order a Theatre be erected in the Church-yard of <hi>Noſtre Dame,</hi> big enough to receive all the Nobility and Clergy in the Town: Let this Theatre, if your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty think good, be hung with Cloath of Gold, and other rich Stuffs, and an Altar ſet up in the middle on Sunday next; I would deſire your Majeſty to be there, with all the Princes and Nobility in <hi>Paris,</hi> and after a grand Maſs is ſung, let the Princeſs be brought alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beſides this, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:35775:84"/>there ſhould be twenty perſons at leaſt, with Trumpets, Horns, Drums, Hoboys and Symbals, ready in ſome by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, when I throw up my Cap into the air, to advance towards the Theatre with all the noiſe they can make; which Muſick, with ſome other ingredients that I have, will I hope ſend the Devil pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Princeſs: The King gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all things ſhould be done as <hi>Matteo</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted; and Sunday being come, and the Theatre throng'd with a multitude of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of quality, and the Church-yard of <hi>Noſtre Dame</hi> full of people, the Princeſs was led in by two Biſhops, and followed by ſeveral Lords of the Court; <hi>Roderick</hi> was in a terrible amaze, to behold ſo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent a preparation, and pondering with himſelf, was over-heard to pronounce theſe words: I would fain know what this raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Peaſant means to do; I have ſeen many places, I have more than once ſeen the whole pomp of Heaven, nor am I ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what is moſt formidable in Hell, yet can I not tell what to make of this; but I'le handle him like a Rogue, as he is, and if I fail, <hi>Pluto</hi> requite me; <hi>Matteo</hi> came up cloſe to him, and deſired him very
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:35775:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>civilly to depart; but <hi>Roderick</hi> cryed out, Oh the wonderous cunning that is in you! do you think by this whimſey to ſave your ſelf from my power, and the indignation of the King? but think what you will, you ſcoundrel, I am reſolv'd you ſhall, hang for't, or elſe let me paſs for the moſt miſerable poor-ſpirited Devil in the World; <hi>Matteo</hi> perſiſted in his requeſt, but <hi>Belphegor</hi> gave him worſe Language than before; but all that frighted not <hi>Matteo,</hi> for without loſing more time, he threw his hat up into the air, and at an inſtant the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, Horns, and all the reſt of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick ſtruck up, and advanc'd towards the Theatre; <hi>Roderick</hi> was ſtartled at the noiſe, and made it manifeſt that there are ſome Devils as fearfull as men, and not able to imagine the reaſon, he called out to <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teo,</hi> and ask'd what was the matter? <hi>Matteo</hi> being a cunning Rogue every inch of him, as if he had been terribly frighted, informs him thus: Alas! poor <hi>Roderick,</hi> ſays he, 'tis your Wife <hi>Honeſta</hi> is come to ſeek you at <hi>Paris;</hi> he ſaid no more, but it is not to be imagined what diſorder theſe four or five words put the Devil into; they took away his wit and judgement, ſo as
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:35775:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>without any conſideration, whether the news was poſſible or not, without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one word, away he ſtole from the Princeſs; chooſing rather to go back into Hell, and give up his accounts there, than to return again into the thraldom of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that had already coſt him ſo many ſorrows and dangers. As ſoon as he arrived, he demanded audience, and in the preſence of <hi>Pluto, Aecus, Minos,</hi> and <hi>Radamanthus,</hi> all of them Counſellors of State, he declared that the Souls of Men were in the right on't, and that 'twas their Wives that ſent them to Hell: <hi>Matteo</hi> that had been too crafty for the Devil, returns to <hi>Florence</hi> in great triumph; the Chronicle mentions not any great matter the King gave him, but it ſays, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gain'd ſufficiently by the two former, he eſteemed himſelf very happy that he had eſcaped hanging at <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
